<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>An Apology for the English Presbyterians with a defence of the heads of agreement assented to by the united ministers in the year 91.</title>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1699</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 113 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 44 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A25697</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing A3548</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R17890</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">12728448</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 12728448</idno>
            <idno type="VID">66396</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A25697)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 66396)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 374:1)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>An Apology for the English Presbyterians with a defence of the heads of agreement assented to by the united ministers in the year 91.</title>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], [vi], 79 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed and are to be sold by the booksellers of London and Westminster,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1699.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Errata on p. [vi].</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Presbyterian Church --  England --  Government.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-12</date>
            <label>Simon Charles</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:66396:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:66396:1"/>
            <p>AN APOLOGY FOR THE <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> WITH A DEFENCE OF THE Heads of Agreement Aſſented to by the <hi>
                  <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Miniſters,</hi> in the Year 91.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON,</hi> Printed, and are to be Sold by the Bookſellers of <hi>London</hi> and <hi>Weſtminſter,</hi> 1699.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="to_the_reader">
            <pb facs="tcp:66396:2"/>
            <pb n="i" facs="tcp:66396:2"/>
            <head>TO THE READER.</head>
            <p>IN the Reigns of Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> and <hi>James</hi> the <hi>Firſt,</hi> the <hi>Engliſh Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> were repreſented to be for ſuch a <hi>Church-Government</hi> as was Inconſiſtent with, and Deſtructive of the King's Supremacy in Matters Eccleſiaſtical, as well as of the <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan</hi> Form. And that the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> might be induc'd to Believe it, Three Articles were propoſed to be Subſcribed unto; the <hi>Firſt</hi> about the <hi>Supremacy,</hi> the other <hi>Two</hi> about the <hi>Government, Liturgy,</hi> and <hi>Ceremonies</hi> of the Church; whereupon they, who refuſed Subſcripti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on only to the <hi>Second</hi> and <hi>Third,</hi> were ſaid to do ſo, becauſe they would not Allow of the <hi>Firſt.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>This <hi>Accuſation</hi> was the more generally Receiv'd, becauſe the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians</hi> Correſponded with their Brethren in <hi>Scotland,</hi> (who deny the <hi>Supremacy</hi>) about Epiſcopacy, the Liturgy, and the Ceremonies; and among the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>forming Clergy,</hi> there were ſome, who would have introduced the <hi>Claſſical</hi> Government,
<pb n="ii" facs="tcp:66396:3"/> under the <hi>Name</hi> of <hi>Dioceſan;</hi> which moved Archbiſhop <hi>Bancroft</hi> to Publiſh his <hi>Scotizing Dangerous Poſitions and Survey.</hi> Beſides the <hi>Claſſical</hi> National Government being found<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed on a <hi>Divine Right,</hi> was the more frightful to the <hi>Queen,</hi> her Nobility and Gentry, who would never ſuffer the Divine Right of the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan</hi> Government; knowing that the Divine Right of a National Church Government of any ſort, and the <hi>Regal</hi> Supremacy can never <hi>ſimul &amp; ſemel</hi> dwell in the ſame Kingdom, the <hi>Setting</hi> up of the <hi>One,</hi> being a <hi>Subverſion of the other.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> Obſerving the Nature of the <hi>Accuſation,</hi> and the <hi>Arts,</hi> uſed to inſinuate the Belief of it into the Minds of their <hi>Governours,</hi> judg'd it neceſſary to do their Part to clear themſelves from thoſe Impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tations, which they did, in their <hi>Proteſtations, Petitions,</hi> and other <hi>Writings,</hi> by a Free, Open and <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>ndiſguiſed Repreſentation of their <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples</hi> about the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of Particular Churches; and alſo a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bout the King<hi>'s Supremacy,</hi> making it Evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent, that in all theſe Points, they agreed en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tirely with the <hi>firſt Reformers,</hi> even with them who ſate up a Church at <hi>Franckfort,</hi> in Queen <hi>Mary's</hi> day; and had a Chief hand, in Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming the Church of <hi>England,</hi> under Queen <hi>Elizabeth,</hi> who ſettled <hi>Parochian Churches</hi> (which for their Form, are the ſame with <hi>Congregational</hi>) as the only Churches of Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution, recognizing all the Superiorities
<pb n="iii" facs="tcp:66396:3"/> and Preheminences which the Dioceſan Biſhop hath above the Presbyter to be only <hi>Jure Regio,</hi> or <hi>Parliamentario,</hi> ſo that as the <hi>Parochian Presbyters</hi> are of God's Institution, the <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſan Biſhop</hi> is of the Prince's making; and accordingly, as every Creator takes care of his own Creature, as God has Provided a Maintainance for the <hi>Presbyter,</hi> the King hath alſo Endowed the Biſhop, which is as I take it, the true reaſon why Sr. <hi>Thomas Ridley,</hi> a Perſon <hi>Zealous</hi> for the Church, in his <hi>View of the Civil and Eccle<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſiaſtical</hi> Laws, Par. 3. Cap. 5. Affirms, <hi>That God hath</hi> by his Word made Tythes due <hi>to Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chian Churches,</hi> but not to <hi>Dioceſan Biſhops, whoſe Indowments ſtood</hi> in <hi>good Tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poral, and Finable Lands,</hi> which <hi>Gratious</hi> Princes, <hi>and other good Benefactors of for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mer Ages</hi> beſtowed upon them.</p>
            <p>The <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians</hi> keeping tightly to thoſe <hi>Principles,</hi> on which the Reformation began, were Eſteemed by the <hi>Nobility,</hi> and <hi>Gentry</hi> to be Men of ſuch <hi>Peaceable Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples</hi> as might be ſafely Indulg'd; who therefore oft in <hi>Parliaments</hi> made Application to the <hi>Prince</hi> on their behalf.</p>
            <p>On theſe <hi>Principles</hi> the late <hi>Union</hi> between the Congregational and Presbyterian was entered into, giving ſo much <hi>Security</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that no <hi>Sincere Approver</hi> of it, can have any hand in ſetting up that Government, which endangers it; Their being for any ſuch <hi>Mo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>del,</hi> is a being for what deſtroys thoſe Churches,
<pb n="iv" facs="tcp:66396:4"/> which they themſelves Believe to be of God's Ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pointment. Nor Indeed can they be for the Divine Inſtitution of any other Particular Churches than what are <hi>Congregational,</hi> unleſs upon this Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple, [That the Catholick-Church-Viſible is a <hi>Govern'd Society,</hi> that hath a Supreme Power under Chriſt, <hi>Monarchical, Ariſtocratical,</hi> or <hi>Democratical,</hi> Authorized to <hi>Govern</hi> the Whole by Legiſlation and Judgment;] Which is a Notion ſo contrary to what not only all true Proteſtants in general, but the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> as well as the <hi>Congregationaliſts</hi> in particular are for, that they deteſt, and abhor it.</p>
            <p>A Clear Conviction of theſe things, upon ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture Deliberation, and a ſerious Obſervation of the Sentiments of our Wiſeſt and moſt kind Friends, with a ſincere Deſire, that my Brethren may be cleared from thoſe Aſperſions, (which either through the <hi>Inadvertency</hi> of ſome of them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, or the Crafty Inſinuations of their Adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaries) hath been caſt upon them, and that they may continue in the Peaceable Injoyment of that <hi>Liberty,</hi> which through the Auſpicious influence of the Government they are Poſſeſſed of, hath moved me to make this <hi>Apologetical</hi> Repre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſentation of their Genuine Principles: Being ſtrongly Perſwaded, that as our <hi>Governours</hi> will conſider the Real difference there is between the Principles of the <hi>Engliſh</hi> and <hi>CLASSICAL</hi> Presbyterians, and notwithſtanding their Indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation against the <hi>Latter,</hi> will always extend their <hi>Generous</hi> and <hi>Chriſtian Compaſſions</hi> to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards the <hi>Former;</hi> So my Brethren of the Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian
<pb n="v" facs="tcp:66396:4"/> Denomination, will give ſome Evident Demonſtrations of their ſincere and Conſtant ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>herence to thoſe <hi>Principles</hi> of the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> as Delivered long ago in their <hi>Proteſtations, &amp;c.</hi> and lately in the <hi>Heads</hi> of Agreement, and Particularly to thoſe <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cles of it,</hi> by which they are ſet at the greateſt Diſtance from Intermedling with the <hi>National Church Form.</hi>
            </p>
            <trailer>Farewel.</trailer>
         </div>
         <div type="errata">
            <pb facs="tcp:66396:5"/>
            <head>ERRATA.</head>
            <p>PAge 49. line 20. for <hi>Eſpecially,</hi> read <hi>Specifically.</hi> p. 61. l. 6. for <hi>as,</hi> read <hi>and;</hi> l. 16. for <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> read <hi>Claſſical.</hi>
            </p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="text">
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:66396:5"/>
            <head>AN APOLOGY FOR THE <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians.</hi>
            </head>
            <div type="introduction">
               <p>THE Prejudices, which are, in the minds of many, againſt the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> in this Kingdom, ariſing from ſome miſtaken No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tions, entertain'd about the <hi>Principles,</hi> which Men of that Denomination are ſaid to embrace, there can't be, I think, a more Effectual Apology made for them, than what is done by an Impartial Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſentation of thoſe Principles they do really own; and what, tho' laid to their Charge, they do with the moſt Indigna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion and Abhorrence diſavow. I will therefore faithfully propoſe <hi>what</hi> the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Presbyterians,</hi> for whom <hi>alone</hi> I make this Plea, <hi>do,</hi> and <hi>do</hi> not, <hi>hold;</hi> And for the greater ſatisfaction of my <hi>Reader,</hi> I
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:66396:6"/> will ſet in the cleareſt Light I can, the Notions eſpouſed by the <hi>Claſſical</hi> or <hi>Scotch Presbyterians,</hi> with which the <hi>Engliſh</hi> could never comply; though upon the Suppoſal, that they are <hi>zealous Defenders</hi> of that <hi>Claſſical</hi> Government, they have fall'n under the Diſpleaſure and Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt of our <hi>Civil</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="1" type="section">
               <head>SECT. I.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>What are the <hi>Principles</hi> about <hi>Church-Government,</hi> held by the <hi>Engliſh Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians,</hi> wherein they do <hi>differ</hi> from the <hi>Claſſical-Scotch-Presbyterians.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.1. THE <hi>Principles</hi> held by the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Presbyterians</hi> about the <hi>Conſtitution,</hi> and Power of Particular Churches, and their Subordination to the Civil Magiſtrate, are briefly theſe.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That a Governing Church is of no larger Extent than a Worſhipping Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Ruling Power of their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers is not to be ſtretch'd beyond the Bounds and Limits of their Worſhipping Congregation.</p>
                  <pb n="3" facs="tcp:66396:6"/>
                  <p n="3">3. That what Power beſides this is re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiſite to reform the Diſorders in Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Churches, ſuch as the Removing Scandalous and Heretical Teachers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> is veſted in the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="4">4. That it belongs alſo to the Civil Magiſtrate to convene Synods, or Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of Miniſters, when there ſhall be an occaſion for them, whoſe Power, when convened, is only <hi>Perſuaſive,</hi> not <hi>Coercive.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.2. The Principles, which the <hi>Claſſical</hi> or <hi>Scotch Presbyterians,</hi> who aſſert the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of a <hi>National Church-Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> do advance, are,</p>
                  <p n="1">1. That <hi>One Governing</hi> Church is made up of <hi>many worſhipping</hi> Congregations.</p>
                  <p n="2">2. That the Ruling Power of their Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ficers is extended beyond the Bounds of a ſingle Congregation. For, by aſſerting the Catholick Church Viſible to be a <hi>Govern'd Society,</hi> or <hi>Organnick Body,</hi> they muſt ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſarily, and do profeſſedly own, that the Miniſtry, Ordinances, and Cenſures are given firſtly to the Catholick Church Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible, and ſecondarily to particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, which, whether Congregational, Claſſical, Provincial. <hi>&amp;c.</hi> are not <hi>properly</hi> Churches, but only <hi>Parts</hi> or <hi>Members</hi>
                     <pb n="4" facs="tcp:66396:7"/> diverſly combin'd) of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> which is the only proper Viſible Church, whereupon all Church-Power is habitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally ſeated in the Officers of the <hi>Catholick Church Viſible,</hi> as <hi>ſuch,</hi> and therefore ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended beyond the Bounds of ſingle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, even to the utmoſt Limits of the Catholick Church Viſible.</p>
                  <p n="3">3. That the Ruling Officers in their lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Aſſemblies, <hi>viz. Claſſical, Provincial, National, Patriarchal,</hi> and <hi>Oecumenical,</hi> have a Power inherent in them to reform the Diſorders of particular Churches, and to remove ſcandalous or Heretical Teachers.</p>
                  <p n="4">4. That it belongs to the Church and not to the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> to convene Synods or Aſſemblies of Miniſters and other Ruling Officers.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.3. In theſe particular Inſtances, you have a full, though brief Account of what is embraced by the <hi>Engliſh,</hi> and by the <hi>Claſſical Presbyterians.</hi> And it's now my Part to <hi>vindicate</hi> the <hi>former</hi> from thoſe Reproaches unjuſtly caſt upon them, and ſhew that the Charge can not be fairly laid at the Door of any <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> but the <hi>Claſſical.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="5" facs="tcp:66396:7"/>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.4. That I may do the <hi>Engliſh Preſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> Juſtice, in the repreſenting their Principles I muſt conſider what the miſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rable State of the Church was before <hi>Lu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther;</hi> upon what Principles the Prote<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtants went in their Endeavours to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>form the Church; and then evince, that the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians</hi> ſtuck firmly to thoſe Principles, upon which the Separa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion was made from the Church of <hi>Rome.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="section">
               <head>SECT. II.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Miſerable State of the Church before <hi>Luther,</hi> the <hi>Principles</hi> on which the Reformation was begun and carryed on, with a ſtate of the Controverſie between <hi>Papiſt,</hi> and <hi>Proteſtant.</hi> The <hi>Engliſh</hi> Presbyterians conſtantly adhered to the <hi>Reformed</hi> about Church-Government, particularly <hi>Cartwright</hi> &amp;c.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.1. ABout the time that <hi>Luther</hi> with many others endeavour'd a Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation of the Church, the Great Evil complained of was the Intolerable <hi>Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny</hi> of the Eccleſiaſticks. The People were then ſo very much under the Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er of the Clergy, that they were perfect
<pb n="6" facs="tcp:66396:8"/> Strangers to the leaſt Part of Chriſtian Liberty, beſides, the Inferiour Clergy ſo grievouſly Oppreſſed by their Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ours, and all ſo much Slaves to the Plea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure of the greateſt, that throughout all <hi>Europe,</hi> the Miſeries of the People were ſo great and preſſing, that none durſt open their Mouths in favour of their Ancient Rights, and Privileges. Yea,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.2. The <hi>Domination,</hi> and <hi>Tyranny</hi> of Popiſh Prelates, who aimed more at Worldly Grandeur, than at the advan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cing Chriſt's Glory, was grown to ſuch a Height, that they did what-ever was good in their own Eyes, and that they might do it with the grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Countenance, they aſſerted, that there was a Catholick Church Viſible; that this Catholick Viſible Church was One Governed Corporation, or Society, under one ſupreme Governing Power, to which they aſcended by ſundry ſteps, from the Dioceſane to the Provincial, from thence to the Patriarchal.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.3. The firſt Reformers, as many of their Fore-Fathers, ſuch as the <hi>Wicklif<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fiſts, Huſſiſts,</hi> &amp;c. groaning under theſe Inſupportable Burdens, and throughly
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:66396:8"/> underſtanding from whence they had their Riſe, laid the Ax to the Root of the <hi>Antichriſtian</hi> Tyranny, denying that there was a <hi>Catholick Church Viſible.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.4. Here the Reformed fix'd their Foot, affirming, that the Univerſal Church was made up only of <hi>Elect Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lievers,</hi> and was <hi>Inviſible:</hi> that thoſe ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Privileges, which the <hi>Papiſts</hi> appro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>priated to their Catholick Church Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, belonged only to the <hi>Inviſible</hi> Church, and hereby left no foundation for the raiſing a Catholick Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment upon, for <hi>Sublato Fundamento tolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur Opus,</hi> and thus their Catholick Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment fell to the Ground. The Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, in Controverſie, being <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal,</hi> as well as Catholick, muſt have a Viſible as well as a Catholick Church for its <hi>State;</hi> ſo that where no ſuch <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church,</hi> there can be no ſuch <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Government.</hi> On the other hand,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.5. The <hi>Papiſts</hi> being fully convinced that the <hi>Reformers</hi> had taken the moſt effectual way to ſubvert their Church Government, and diveſt them of that Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority they aſſumed to themſelves over the Conſciences of the People, owned it,
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:66396:9"/> and in Oppoſition unto them, held that there was a <hi>Catholick Church Viſible,</hi> under an External Polity, or Government. So <hi>Alphonſus a Caſtro adverſ. Haereſ.</hi> Lib. 1. <q rend="inline">The <hi>Wickliffiſts, Huſſiſts,</hi> and <hi>Lutheranes</hi> do ſtifly inſiſt on the Inviſibility of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> and is the ſtrongeſt Shield they have to defend themſelves againſt whatever is urged from the <hi>Church's Authority,</hi> which is the ſharpeſt Weapon we can uſe againſt them.</q> 
                     <hi>Gre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gory de Valentina Anal. Fid. Cathol. lib.</hi> 6. <hi>Chap.</hi> 3. <q rend="inline">If the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal Church</hi> be Compoſed only of thoſe who are <hi>Predeſtinated,</hi> and <hi>truly Righteous,</hi> the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church of <hi>Rome</hi> can never be defended.</q> And <hi>Rodericus de Arriago</hi> confeſſeth, (<hi>de Divin. ſid. Diſp.</hi> 7. §. 1. <hi>Num.</hi> 3.) <hi>That the true Reaſon, why they lay ſo much ſtreſs upon this</hi> Part <hi>of the</hi> Controverſie, <hi>is becauſe the</hi> Support <hi>of the</hi> Papall Power <hi>Depends upon it.</hi> Many other Authorities may be at any time produced for the Confirmation of this Point, but the thing it ſelf is ſo clear that it's not needful.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.6. The Reformed in this Kingdom agree'd with the <hi>Wickliffiſts, Huſſiſts,</hi> and <hi>Lutheranes,</hi> owning that the Catholick
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:66396:9"/> Church was no otherwiſe <hi>viſible,</hi> than as it might be ſeen in Particular Church-Aſſemblies, which cloſely examined a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mounts to more, than that there is no Church, <hi>properly</hi> ſpeaking, <hi>Viſible,</hi> but what is Particular, and no <hi>External</hi> Church-Government but what is <hi>ſeated</hi> in Particular Churches; that the Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ming ſuch <hi>Diſorders,</hi> as cannot be done by that Power which is Peculiar to <hi>Paro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiall,</hi> or <hi>Congregational</hi> Churches, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>longs to the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate, viz.</hi> ſuch as the convening the Aſſemblies of Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters, and the removing Scandalous, Turbulent, and Heretical Teachers. But</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.7. If all that Power, which is <hi>meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Spiritual</hi> and <hi>Eccleſiaſtical,</hi> be appropri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ated to <hi>particular</hi> Congregations, then all that Power exerciſed in <hi>Claſſical, Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſane, Provincial, National, Patriarchal,</hi> and <hi>Oecumenical</hi> Synods or Aſſemblies, falls to the ground, together with their having <hi>Authority</hi> to determine Controverſies of Faith; for <hi>ſublato fundamento tollitur opus,</hi> as has been already obſerved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.8. This being for many Years after the Reformation began in this Land, ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally received, the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians</hi>
                     <pb n="10" facs="tcp:66396:10"/> took Advantage againſt that Part of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which retaining too much of the Catholick Church Leven, would fain have preſerved ſomewhat of the old Papal Power. Some feeble Efforts were put forth in the Reign of Queen <hi>Elizabeth</hi> and <hi>James</hi> the Firſt, but <hi>re infecta;</hi> and in the Reign of <hi>Charles</hi> the Firſt, by the help of Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi> and his Followers, great Advancements were made towards the Reſtoring this Power; But</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.9. The general Vogue of the <hi>Epiſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pal,</hi> as well as the Cry of the <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> being againſt the Exerciſe of any ſuch Power, the Difficulties the Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop met with were next to inſuperable; eſpecially upon the account of the Diffe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent Copies, about the Twentieth <hi>Arti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cle</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> for as ſome Copies begin <hi>thus,</hi> 
                     <q rend="inline">[The Church hath Power to decree Rites and Cere<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monies and <hi>Authority</hi> in <hi>Controverſies of Faith,</hi> it is not Lawfull <hi>&amp;c.</hi>]</q> So others begin at, [<hi>It is not Lawfull,</hi> &amp;c.] Where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon <hi>Laud</hi>'s Party found it neceſſary to oppugn the old Doctrine about the Au<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thority and Government of the Church, and whereas the 20th Article in ſome
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:66396:10"/> Ancient Copies of the Queen's Reign be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gan at, [<hi>It is not Lawfull for the Church to Ordain any thing that is contrary to God's Word,</hi> &amp;c.] 'twas ſuch an obſtacle in the way of their Deſigns, that they were hard put to it, and found it neceſſary, if poſſible, to remove it. And accordingly</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.10. Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> a chief Inſtrument in this Deſign, did on the 24th day of <hi>April, Ann.</hi> 1627. anſwer in the Divinity-Schools at <hi>Oxon,</hi> upon theſe two Queſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, <hi>viz.</hi> (1.) <hi>An Eccleſia unquam fuit in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſibilis?</hi> And (2.) <hi>An Eccleſia poſſit er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rare?</hi> Both which he determined in the <hi>Negative.</hi> And in ſtating of the firſt, he fell upon a different way from that of Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> in his Lecture, <hi>De Viſibi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litate Eccleſiae,</hi> and other <hi>Tractates</hi> of and about that time, in which the <hi>Viſibility</hi> of the Church, was no otherwiſe proved, than as ſcattered amongſt the <hi>Waldenſes, Wickliffiſts, Huſſiſts,</hi> &amp;c. For <hi>Heylin,</hi> not liking this manner of Proceeding, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe it utterly diſcontinued the Succeſſion in the Eccleſiaſtical Hierarchy choſe ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to look for a <hi>Continual Viſible Church,</hi> in <hi>Aſia, Ethiopia, Greece, Italy,</hi> and <hi>Rome</hi> it ſelf.</p>
                  <pb n="12" facs="tcp:66396:11"/>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.11. In the Year 1633. <hi>Heylin</hi> was at <hi>Oxon</hi> to Anſwer for his <hi>Degree</hi> of <hi>Doctor,</hi> and inſiſted on the <hi>Authority</hi> of the Church, as formerly he did on the <hi>Infallibility,</hi> and <hi>Viſibility</hi> of it. His Queſtions were (1.) <hi>An Eccleſia habeat Authoritatem in Decer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nendis fidei Controverſiis?</hi> (2.) <hi>Interpretan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>di Scripturas?</hi> (3.) <hi>Decernendi Ritus &amp; Ceremonias?</hi> all which he held in the <hi>Affirmative;</hi> declaring it to be the <hi>Plain</hi> and <hi>Poſitive</hi> Doctrine of the Church of <hi>England</hi> in the 20th Article, which runs thus, <hi>in terminis</hi> viz. <hi>Habet Eccleſia Ritus</hi> ſive <hi>Ceremonias ſtatuendi Jus, &amp; in fidei Controverſiis Authoritatem:</hi> But,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.12. Dr. <hi>Prideaux,</hi> then in the Chair, expreſſed great Diſſatisfaction with <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> charging him with falſifying the Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Doctrine of the Church, as others accuſed <hi>Laud</hi> and other Biſhops, for ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king this Addition, the better to ſupport their <hi>Power</hi> and <hi>Tyranny.</hi> But, ſaith <hi>Hey<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lin,</hi> in his <hi>Examen Hiſtoricum,</hi> 
                     <q rend="inline">Archbi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop <hi>Laud</hi> in his <hi>Speech</hi> in the <hi>Star-Chamber, June</hi> 15. 1637. made it ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pear, that the ſaid Clauſe was in a Printed Book of Articles, publiſhed in the Year 1563. being but very few
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:66396:11"/> Months after they had paſſed in the Convocation, which was on the 29th of <hi>January,</hi> 1562. in the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count; and more than ſo, he ſhewed unto the Lords a Copy of the 20th Article, exemplified out of the <hi>Records,</hi> and atteſted by the hands of a Pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Notary, in which that very Clauſe was found, which had been charged upon the Biſhops for an Innovation. And thus much I can ſay of my own Knowledge, that having occaſion to conſult the Records of Convocation, I found this controverted Clauſe <hi>verba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tim,</hi> in theſe following words; <hi>Habet Ec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cleſia Ritus ſtatuendi Jus, &amp; in fidei Contro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſiis Authoritatem,</hi>
                     </q> ſo far Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> p. 144. who further adds, <q rend="inline">That in the Year 1571, (the <hi>Puritan</hi> Faction begin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning to grow very ſtrong) the Articles were again Printed in <hi>Latin</hi> and <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh,</hi> and this Clauſe left out, Publiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to thoſe Copies in the <hi>Harmony of Confeſſions,</hi> Printed at <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neva, Ann.</hi> 1612. That the Archbiſhop in his Speech, <hi>p.</hi> 71. was of this Opi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion too.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:66396:12"/>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.13. There was, we ſee, a great deal of ſtreſs laid on this Clauſe of the 20th Article, becauſe the Aſſertion, that <hi>the Church hath Authority in Controverſies of Faith,</hi> is ſo neceſſary to <hi>National</hi> and lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger Synods and Aſſemblies, and the lay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing aſide this Clauſe ſo accommodated to the Principles on which the Reformation was begun and carried on. For which reaſon I will offer what I know of this matter, and therein be very impartial.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.14. (1.) That this Clauſe is not either in the <hi>Latin</hi> or <hi>Engliſh</hi> Copies, Printed <hi>Ann.</hi> 1571. is granted by Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> and I have by me a Copy in <hi>Latin,</hi> publiſhed by <hi>John Day, Ann.</hi> 1575. in which 'tis not. (2.) I have ſeen a Copy, <hi>Ann.</hi> 1563. in which it is, and ſo it may be in the <hi>Records</hi> of the Convocations, as has been ſuggeſted, for ought that I do know to the contrary. However (3.) I do affirm upon my own Knowledge, and in moſt humble manner addreſs my ſelf to the preſent Archbiſhop of <hi>Canterbury,</hi> who was of <hi>C. C. C. C.</hi> to Dr. <hi>Green, Maſter,</hi> and to the worthy <hi>Fellows</hi> of that Colledge, for their concurrent Teſtimony, that in the <hi>Manuſcript</hi> Library, given to that
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:66396:12"/> Houſe by Archbiſhop <hi>Matthew Parker,</hi> there are the <hi>Articles</hi> of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which I can't call <hi>thirty nine</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe they are more) ſubſcribed by the Biſhops, in the Year 1562. with the num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber of Pages, and of every Line in each Page in which the Articles are; and that the <hi>twentieth</hi> Article is exactly the ſame with the <hi>twenty first</hi> of <hi>Edward</hi> VI. with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out this Clauſe; whence I conclude, <hi>firſt,</hi> That the leaving of it out being, as is acknowledged by Archbiſhop <hi>Laud</hi> and Dr. <hi>Heylin,</hi> moſt adjuſted to the Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples of the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi> the true and genuine Reaſon is, becauſe the firſt Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formers of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> and the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> were of a mind in this Particular, and oppoſed the Papal Tyran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny upon the ſame Foundation. <hi>Secondly,</hi> That although in the beginning of the Queen there were ſome otherwiſe mind<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, who added this Clauſe to the Copy of 1563. yet the Biſhops unanimouſly ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hered to the Copy which laid this Clauſe aſide. But to return; It is manifeſt,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.15. That the Old <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> whom I call <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> being firm Adherers unto the firſt Reformers, did in their Oppoſition to the <hi>Papal Ty<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ranny,</hi>
                     <pb n="16" facs="tcp:66396:13"/> hold, <hi>first,</hi> That there was no pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per Viſible Church, but what was Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular; <hi>ſecondly,</hi> That Particular Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches were of the ſame Extent with Sin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Congregations; and the Power of thoſe in Office was confined to the Li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mits of a ſingle Congregation.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.16. The Learned Mr. <hi>Cartwright,</hi> a Perſon of that eſteem amongſt the <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformiſts</hi> in the Reign of the Queen, as to be choſen by them to defend their Principles againſt Dr. <hi>Whtgift,</hi> expreſſing their ſenſe with much Freedom and Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, I need inſiſt on no other to prove what I affirm of them; and who-ever is converſant with the Books then written, will ſee, that their Authors ſo generally and frequently refer'd themſelves to his Writings; and ſo conſtantly undertook his <hi>Defence</hi> as to be ſatisfied, that the mentioning what was preſſed by others is altogether unneceſſary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.17. This Learned <hi>Cartwright,</hi> wri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting in <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Admonition</hi> tot he <hi>Parliament,</hi> (Publiſhed in the Year 1572. Anſwered by Dr. <hi>Whitgift,</hi>) doth not only make a <hi>Reply</hi> to that <hi>Anſwer,</hi> which was in the Year 1574. defended by <hi>Whit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gift;</hi>
                     <pb n="17" facs="tcp:66396:13"/> But in his <hi>Reply</hi> to this <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Anſwer, Anno</hi> 1575. expreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf fully to this effect, I both mention <hi>Cartwright</hi>'s <hi>Reply</hi> to <hi>Whitgift</hi>'s <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Anſwer,</hi> and do inculcate it, becauſe <hi>Fuller, Heylin,</hi> and <hi>Walton,</hi> have told the World, that the <hi>Defence</hi> of the <hi>Anſwer</hi> kept the Field with all the Marks of an abſolute Victory; whereas it's moſt mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt, that <hi>Cartwright</hi> made a <hi>Reply</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto in <hi>two Parts,</hi> the <hi>Firſt, Anno</hi> 1575. and <hi>Anno</hi> 1577. he Publiſhed the reſt. And what is Remarkable, <hi>Fuller,</hi> in the ſame or very next Page, where he ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fidently avers, that <hi>Cartwright</hi> never Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed to the <hi>Second Anſwer,</hi> doth himſelf refer to the firſt part of the <hi>Reply,</hi> that was made unto it. See his <hi>Church Hiſt. Cent.</hi> 16. <hi>l.</hi> 9. <hi>p.</hi> 102. Now in the firſt Part of this <hi>ſecond Reply, Cartwright</hi> fully Confirms the Truth of my Aſſertion, <q rend="inline">That <hi>every Particular Church</hi> ſhould have her <hi>Biſhop,</hi> is manifeſt by <hi>Paul</hi> to <hi>Timothy.</hi> For ſeeing the Diſcription of a Biſhop which he gives doth <hi>Agree</hi> unto the Miniſter of every <hi>Congregation,</hi> and nothing there requir'd in <hi>the</hi> one, which is not in the <hi>other,</hi> it follows, that the <hi>Miniſter of every Congregation</hi> is the <hi>Biſhop</hi> thereof. For the Deſcription
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:66396:14"/> agreeing with every of them, the things deſcribed muſt likewiſe. Secondly, un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leſs he do by this deſcription of the Bi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhop ſet forth the nature of every Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſter of the Word in his Congregation, in deſcribing the Offices of the Church he has left out the <hi>Principaleſt</hi> Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers, and was more careful in deſcribing the <hi>Deacons</hi> Miniſtry, not occupied in the Word, than the teaching Miniſtries, But that is abſurd; it muſt follow that he underſtood them by the name of <hi>Biſhop:</hi> Furthermore St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s <hi>Biſhop</hi> was appointed to the ſame <hi>Place,</hi> where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>unto his <hi>Deacons:</hi> But his <hi>Deacons</hi> were aſſigned to a <hi>Particular Congregation</hi> — St. <hi>Paul</hi> alſo there aſſigning the Charge and Care of the <hi>Biſhop</hi> over the <hi>Church</hi> of God, muſt either give him Charge over the <hi>Whole Body</hi> of the <hi>Catholick Church,</hi> or over <hi>One Particular Congregation;</hi> or of the <hi>Faithfull Company</hi> of <hi>one Houſe:</hi> But he extendeth not the Charge over <hi>all the Catholick Church,</hi> for that were to make a <hi>Pope</hi> not a <hi>Biſhop;</hi> nor reſtrain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth him to the Faithful of one Houſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hold, conſidering that he oppoſeth the Government of his <hi>Houſe</hi> to the <hi>Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> of the Church: It followeth there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore that he appointeth him to one <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:66396:14"/> Church.</hi> That by this <hi>Word [Church]</hi> muſt be underſtood <hi>one</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> three Significations, it ſtandeth upon this Ground; that in none of St. <hi>Paul</hi>'s other Epiſtles, or St. <hi>Luke</hi>'s Writings, that word <hi>[Church]</hi> is ever uſed other<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wiſe; and never ſignifieth the <hi>Church,</hi> either of a <hi>Province</hi> or <hi>Dioceſe, Rep.</hi> 2. <hi>Part.</hi> 1. <hi>p.</hi> 360. and in <hi>page</hi> 687. ſaith he, I have ſhewed that Scripture uſeth not to call a <hi>Province</hi> or <hi>Dioceſe,</hi> a <hi>Church,</hi> but either the whole <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal,</hi> or elſe a <hi>Particular Congregation.</hi> Thus you ſee how Mr. <hi>Cartwright</hi> doth, not only hold a <hi>Presbyter</hi> and a <hi>Biſhop</hi> to be the ſame office, but that the office of a Presbyter is <hi>Appropriated</hi> to a <hi>ſingle Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregatio,</hi> and that the Holy Scripture never ſpeakes of a <hi>Dioceſane</hi> or <hi>Provincial</hi> Church, but only of the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal</hi> (which is Inviſible) and a <hi>Particular Church,</hi> and therefore not of a <hi>Claſſical Church.</hi>
                     </q> But</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.18. What I ſhall offer from the mul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>titude of <hi>Nonconformists,</hi> whoſe Sorrows encreaſed on <hi>James</hi> the Firſt's coming to the <hi>Engliſh</hi> Throne, will evidence what I affirm to Perſons of the meaneſt Capa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cities. For Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> who gathered up the ſence of theſe Old <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi>
                     <pb n="20" facs="tcp:66396:15"/> whom he ſtyles, in his Preface to his <hi>Engliſh Puritaniſm, [Rigid Presbyterians,]</hi> declared poſitively, that they Hold and Maintain, <q rend="inline">That every <hi>Company, Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation,</hi> and Aſſembly of true Believers, joining together according to the Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der of the Goſpel, in the <hi>true Worſhip of God,</hi> is a <hi>true Viſible</hi> Church of Chriſt; and that the ſame Title [<hi>viz.</hi> of <hi>True Viſible Church</hi>] is <hi>Improperly</hi> given to other Societies, Combinations, or Aſſemblies whatſoever — That Chriſt Jeſus hath not <hi>Subjected</hi> any Church, or Congregation of his to any other Superiour Eccleſiaſtical Juriſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diction than unto <hi>that</hi> which is <hi>within it. ſelf.</hi> So that if a whole Church, or Congregation, ſhall err in any Matter of Faith, and Religion, no other <hi>Churches,</hi> or <hi>Spiritual Church-Officers,</hi> have (by any Warrant from the Word of God,) Power to <hi>Cenſure,</hi> Puniſh or <hi>Controul</hi> the ſame: But are only to <hi>Counſel,</hi> or <hi>Adviſe</hi> the ſame, and leave their <hi>Souls</hi> to the immediate Judgment of Chriſt, and their Bodies to the Sword and Power of the CIVIL MAGISTRATE, who alone upon Earth hath Power to Puniſh a whole Church or Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion — They hold, that every Eſtab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liſhed
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:66396:15"/> Church ought (as a ſpecial Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogative, wherewith ſhe is endowed by Jeſus ChriſT) to have Power and Liberty to chooſe their own Spiritual and Eccleſaiſtical Officers — They hold and believe the <hi>EQuality</hi> in Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction, and Authority of Church<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es and Church-Miniſters, is no more <hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rogatory</hi> and Repugnant to the <hi>State</hi> and Glory of a Monarch, than the Parity and Equality of School-Maſters or Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters of Families.</q> 
                     <hi>Chap.</hi> 2. §. 1. 5. 11. There was alſo about this time a Proteſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the Kings Supremacy made in the Name of the Afflicted Miniſters, in which they declare. <q rend="inline">That they confine, and bound all Eccleſiaſtical Power within the Limits only of one Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregation; holding, that the greateſt Eccleſiaſtical Power ought not to ſtretch beyond the ſame: And that it is an ARROGATING PRINCELY <hi>Supre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>macy,</hi> for any Eccleſaiſtical Perſon or Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons whoſoever, to take upon themſelves Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction over many Churches — That it is utterly unlaw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful for any one Miniſter to take upon himſelf, or accept of a ſole Ecleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Juriſdiction over ſo much as one Congregation. And therefore ſome of
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:66396:16"/> the moſt Honeſt and Godly in the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation, ought to be adjoined to the Miniſter, in the Spiritual Regiment of the Souls of the Congregation, of which he is a Paſtor — That thoſe Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Perſons, that make claim to greater Power and Authority than this, eſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally they that make claim <hi>Jure Divino,</hi> of Power, or Juriſdiction to meddle with other Churches than that one Congregation, of which they are or ought to be <hi>Members,</hi> do USURP UPON THE SUREMACY OF THE CIVIL MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GISTRATE.</q> §. 24, 25, 27. And a little before, §. 12. <q rend="inline">We hold that the King has Power to <hi>Remove</hi> out of the Churches, all <hi>Scandalous, Schiſmatical,</hi> and <hi>Hereti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Teachers.</hi>
                     </q> And, §. 14. <q rend="inline">That the King only hath Power within his Dominions to Convene Synods, or <hi>General Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies</hi> of <hi>Miniſters.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.9. Soon after this Proteſtation, a <hi>Chriſtian,</hi> and <hi>Modest Offer</hi> of a <hi>most In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>different Conference,</hi> or Diſputation about the Main and Principal Controverſies be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt the Prelates, and the late Silenced Miniſters in <hi>England,</hi> was made; in which, <hi>viz. P.</hi> 2, 3. the <hi>Nonconforming</hi> Miniſters undertook to prove, <q rend="inline">That
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:66396:16"/> there is no <hi>true Viſible</hi> Church of Chriſt, but <hi>a Particular</hi> Ordinary <hi>Congregation only;</hi> that every true <hi>Viſible</hi> Church of Chriſt, or Ordinary Aſſembly of the Faithful, hath by Chriſt's Ordinance, Power in it ſelf, immediately under Chriſt, to <hi>Elect</hi> and <hi>Ordain, Deprive</hi> and <hi>Depoſe</hi> their Miniſters; and to Execute all other <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Cenſures:</hi> That the Paſtor of a Particular Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on is the Higheſt Ordinary Eccleſiaſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cal Officer in any true Conſtituted Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Church of Chriſt: That the <hi>Civil Magiſtrates</hi> ought to be the <hi>Overſeers</hi> of Provinces, and Dioceſes, and of THE SEVERAL CHURCHES THEREIN: And it is their Office and Duty injoyned them by God, to <hi>take Knowledge,</hi> to <hi>Pu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſh</hi> and Redreſs all Miſgoverning, or ill Treating of any Church, or Church-Officer.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.10. What is here affirm'd by theſe Deprived Miniſters is ſo full, not only a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> but <hi>Claſſical</hi> way, that it may tempt ſome to take it for Granted, That whilſt I profeſs to ſet down the Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples of the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> I am only deſcribing the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> in which they will, perhaps, be confirm'd, when
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:66396:17"/> they conſider, that in this ſame Offer it's aſſerted, <q rend="inline">That the <hi>Paſtor</hi> alone ought not to exerciſe Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction over his Church, but others ought to be joyned to him by the Aſſignment of the ſame Church, NEITHER OUGHT HE, AND THEY TO PERFORM ANY <hi>Main,</hi> and <hi>Material Eccleſiaſtical Act,</hi> WITH<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>OUT THE FREE CONSENT OF THE CONGREGATION:</q> However it's very manifeſt, that theſe <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> were far from cloſing with <hi>Browniſm,</hi> as ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pears from what they <hi>Anſwer</hi> to the 11th <hi>Oppoſition,</hi> in which 'tis demanded, <q rend="inline">[Why do they not wholly with the <hi>Browniſts</hi> ſeparate, and get them to <hi>Amſterdam,</hi> to their Holy Brethren there?] Where they Proteſt, that they are Perſuaded, that many of the Conforming Miniſters are true Miniſters of Jeſus Chriſt, in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dowed with Gifts from Heaven for that Holy Function: And that the <hi>Holy Churches,</hi> which they teach are true Churches;</q> which was ſufficient to clear them from the Reproaches of being <hi>Browniſts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.11. And as they ſo freely expreſs their own true Senſe in theſe Matters, ſo it is with an Aſſurance, that none of the
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:66396:17"/> Conformable Clergy were ſo much a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the above-mentioned Aſſertions, which they undertook to maintain, but would rather Cloſe with them, than Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe themſelves to the Laſh of ſuch Pe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nalties as the Deprived Miniſters lay un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der: Their Words are <hi>Pag.</hi> 16, 17. <q rend="inline">The former Propoſitions are ſuch, that there will not be found, (as we are <hi>verily perſwaded</hi> in our Conſciences) <hi>any one Conformable</hi> Miniſter, except he be a <hi>Masked Papist,</hi> that will <hi>Refuſe to ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribe</hi> to ANY ONE OF THEM, if ſo be it would pleaſe the King and State by Law to Urge them thereunto, under ſuch Penalties as the Miniſters are urged to ſubſcribe unto the Articles, deviſed by the Prelates — Yea, we are out of all doubt, that the Prelates them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, if the caſe ſtood but upon the ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving of their <hi>Temporalities,</hi> (which elſe they ſhould loſe) would <hi>with</hi> HEART, and HAND ſubſcribe to ANY ONE of the aforeſaid Propoſitions.</q> Beſides,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.12. Theſe <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians</hi> were ſo fully convinced of the Truth of the a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid Propoſitions, which they offered to defend, that they were perſwaded they were ſuch, that if the Miniſters ſhould
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:66396:18"/> not conſtantly hold, and maintain the ſame againſt all Men, they cannot ſee how poſſibly (by the Rules of Divinity) the SEPARATION of <hi>our Churches</hi> from the Church of <hi>Rome,</hi> and from the <hi>Pope,</hi> the <hi>Supream Head</hi> thereof, can be Juſtified, <hi>p.</hi> 11. But,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.13. As this offer for a <hi>Conference</hi> was made in the Year 1606, ſo 'twas followed <hi>Anno</hi> 1609, with a Petition of the Depri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved Miniſters, in which they declare themſelves <gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <q rend="inline">As we hold, That your Majeſty within your <hi>Dominions,</hi> have Power to call <hi>Synods,</hi> and to Diſſolve them, ſo we hold likewiſe, that RULING <hi>Synods,</hi> and UNITED <hi>Presbyteries,</hi> ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſing Government and Impoſing Laws and Decrees upon <hi>ſeveral Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches,</hi> and the <hi>Paſtors</hi> of them, are not only <hi>Humane Inſtitutions,</hi> but in regard of the ſaid Government and Authority of <hi>Impoſing Laws altogether</hi> UNLAWFUL, and USURPING <hi>upon</hi> the SUPREMACY <hi>of the Civil</hi> MAGISTRATE — We acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge (as hath been above remembred) no other Power, and Authority for the OVERSEEING, RULING, and Cenſuring of Particular Churches (how many ſoever in number) in the Caſe of their <hi>Miſgovernment,</hi> than that which is <hi>Ori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ginally</hi>
                        <pb n="27" facs="tcp:66396:18"/> Inveſted in <hi>your Royal Perſon,</hi> and from it derived to ſuch of your Laity, as you ſhall Judge Worthy to be De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>puted to the Execution of the ſame un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der you; ſo as the Favour humbly ſollici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted by us is, <hi>That whereas our Lord Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus</hi> hath given to each PARTICULAR CHURCH, or ORDINARY CONGREGA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TION this Right, and Priviledge, <hi>viz. To Elect, Ordain,</hi> and Deprive her own Miniſters; and to Exerciſe all other Parts of <hi>Lawful Eccleſiaſtical Juriſdiction</hi> under him.</q> So far the <hi>Petitioning Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters</hi> (<hi>P.</hi> 13, 14.) who (in <hi>P.</hi> 18.) ſay, <q rend="inline">That in this Church (ſpeaking of a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church, and the Officers there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of) which is <hi>confined within the Bounds of a Pariſh;</hi> one is a <hi>Paſtor,</hi> another a <hi>Teacher,</hi> others <hi>Elders,</hi> and others <hi>Deacons.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.14. Theſe Quotations out of the old <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> do ſufficiently evince, that they held, that <hi>properly</hi> ſpeaking, there was no other Viſible Church, but what was Congregational, that the Power of their Officers is not to be ſtretched beyond the Bounds of a ſingle Congregation; that what Power is needful beſides this, for Reforming Particular Churches, is In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veſted in the Civil Magiſtrate, to whom it doth alſo belong to Convene Synods, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> And it muſt be alſo Remark'd,</p>
                  <pb n="28" facs="tcp:66396:19"/>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.15. That in theſe Inſtances the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Presbyterian,</hi> and the <hi>Congregationalist</hi> are moſt entirely Agreed, as appears, not only from what is in the <hi>Preface</hi> to the <hi>Savoy</hi> Confeſſion, where it's Decla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red by them in theſe Words: <q rend="inline">As for our ſelves we are able to trace the Footſteps of an <hi>Independent Congregational</hi> way, in the Antienteſt Cuſtoms of the Churches, as alſo in the WRITINGS of our ſoundeſt <hi>Proteſtant Divines,</hi> and (that which we are much ſatisfied in) a full Concurrence throughout, in all the Subſtantial Parts of Church-Government with our Reve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rend Brethren, the <hi>Old Puritan Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts</hi> — See <hi>Puritaniſ. Angl.</hi> by Dr. <hi>Ames,</hi> as the Opinions of <hi>Whitehead, Gilbe, Fox, Dearing, Greenham, Cart<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wright, Venner, Fulk, Whitaker, Rai<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds, Perkins,</hi> &amp;c.</q> But alſo from what is in the <hi>Preface</hi> to the <hi>Engliſh Presbytery,</hi> (of which more in due place) where the Author, mentioning Dr. <hi>Ames</hi> his <hi>Puri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taniſm,</hi> adds, <hi>To which</hi> Presbytery <hi>is, at least, a Piece of a Succeſſor.</hi> And thus it continued till the Meeting of the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> of <hi>Divines</hi> at <hi>Weſtminiſter</hi> in the Year 1641, without the putting forth of any Efforts for the Claſſical by <hi>Nonconformiſts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="section">
               <pb n="29" facs="tcp:66396:19"/>
               <head>SECT. III.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The Setting up of the <hi>Claſſical Presbytery</hi> in this Land Attempted by the <hi>Scots,</hi> and by their Intereſts in the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter;</hi> but met with ſo much Oppoſition, not only from the <hi>INDEPENDENTS,</hi> but from ſundry others, that it could never take amongst us.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.1. THE <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dered in Contradiſtinction un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to the <hi>Browniſts,</hi> and other Diſſenters from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> prevailing from the beginning of the Reformation, till the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> at <hi>Weſtminiſter,</hi> met with ſome Check from the Attempts made up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on them, as well as upon the Church of <hi>England</hi> by the <hi>Scots,</hi> and their Influence on the <hi>Aſſembly;</hi> but the <hi>Engliſh Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans</hi> were ſo powerful in this Nation at that time, and the <hi>Independents,</hi> who, in the above-mention'd particulars, Agreed with the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> had obtain'd ſo great an Intereſt in the <hi>Parliament,</hi> and <hi>Army,</hi> and the Multitude of them, who Diſſented from the Church of <hi>England,</hi> DOING SO, upon a Principle that did ſet 'em as much againſt the <hi>Claſſical</hi> Church
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:66396:20"/> Government, the Obſtacles which lay in the way of the Aſſemblies ſetting up the <hi>Claſſical Presbytery,</hi> were ſo many, that they never adventured to Aſſert the Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Right of that <hi>Form;</hi> and the <hi>Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment</hi> would never allow of <hi>all</hi> the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly preſented to 'em. And what was by an <hi>Ordinance</hi> of both Houſes Eſtabliſhed, could never get Reputation enough a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mongſt the People to be generally Recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.2. This being a Point of extraordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nary Importance, in the preſent Caſe, I will be the more Diſtinct in my At<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tempt to clear it. And ſeeing 'tis Granted on all hands, that notwithſtanding the moſt the <hi>Scots</hi> and their Friends either in the <hi>Parliament</hi> or <hi>Aſſembly</hi> could do, the People of this Nation could never be Pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with to Submit to the <hi>Claſſical</hi> Church-Government, I will only ſhew what were the <hi>True</hi> Reaſons, why it could gain no more amongſts us, and the rather, becauſe not only Mr. <hi>Robert Bay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly,</hi> in his <hi>Diſſwaſive</hi> from <hi>Errour,</hi> but alſo the Learned Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> in the <hi>Narrative</hi> he <hi>gives of his own Life, p.</hi> 73. do charge the <hi>Independents</hi> for being the only hinder<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers. Mr. <hi>Bayly</hi> with Unchriſtian bitterneſs,
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:66396:20"/> and ſundry falſe and Rayling Accuſations, ſaith, <q rend="inline">that all the <hi>Prelates</hi> and the <hi>Papiſts</hi> cannot, nor do hinder ſo much the work of <hi>Reformation,</hi> as the five <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſenting</hi> Members, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Independents;</hi>
                     </q> But Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> with more temper, ſaith, <q rend="inline">that the <hi>five Diſſenting</hi> Bretheren, <hi>Joyned with the Reſt till they had Drawn up a</hi> CONFESSION OF FAITH, a <hi>Larger,</hi> and <hi>Shorter Catechiſm;</hi> but when they came to <hi>Church Government</hi> they enga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged them in many long <hi>Debates,</hi> and kept that Buſineſs as long as poſſibly they could, Undetermined; and after that, kept it ſo long <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nexecuted</hi> in al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt all Parts of the Land, ſaving <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don</hi> and <hi>Lancaſhire,</hi> that their Party had time to ſtrengthen themſelves in the Army and the Parliament, and hinder the <hi>Execution</hi> after all, and keep the Government determined of, a ſtran<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger to moſt of the People of this Land, who know it but by <hi>hearſay,</hi> as it was Repreſented by <hi>Reporters.</hi>
                     </q> So far Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who to the ſhame of Mr. <hi>Bayly</hi> (whoſe <hi>Claſſical Zeal</hi> tranſported him him beyond all Bounds of Truth, when he Accuſed the <hi>Independents,</hi> for Patro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nizing all manner of Abominable Er<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rours, and Hereſies,) hath confuted <hi>him,</hi>
                     <pb n="32" facs="tcp:66396:21"/> and done <hi>them</hi> the Juſtice of Leaving it on Record, that they Joyned with the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> in the <hi>Confeſſion of Faith, lar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ger</hi> and <hi>ſhorter Catechiſm.</hi> But</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.3. My deſign is cheifly to clear the Truth and ſhow, that as the <hi>Independents</hi> did undoubtedly their Part to hinder the ſetting up of a National Church-Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which would have Ruined thoſe Churches, which are of Chriſt's Inſtitu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion; ſo <hi>there were others,</hi> who attempted the ſame that the Independents did; for both the <hi>Prelatiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterians</hi> had, upon different Reaſons, their hands in the Oppoſition, and alſo the Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy of the People.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="subsection">
                  <p n="1">§.4. 1. That the <hi>Prelatiſts</hi> had their ſhare in the hindring it, is Apparent from what is in the Letter ſent by the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> to the <hi>Belgick,</hi> and other <hi>Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med</hi> Churches, <hi>p.</hi> 7. in which they de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clare, <q rend="inline">That in thoſe Troubleſome times the <hi>Honourable Houſes of Parliament</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led the Aſſembly to give them their beſt Counſels for the Reformation of the Church, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> — And in this Work (ſay they) we are now excerciſed, tho' the
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:66396:21"/> 
                        <hi>Enemy hath ſtirred up the Heart of our Dear,</hi> and <hi>Dread Sovereign</hi> AGAINST us.</q> Now, it's well known that none ſo Pow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erful with the King, as the Church of <hi>England,</hi> who did, you ſee, their moſt to prevent the Aſſemblies erecting the Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical Government, by ſetting his Majeſty againſt them. But,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="subsection">
                  <p n="2">§.5. 2. The great Impediment that lay in their way, was the Power of the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Presbyterians,</hi> who had Leaven'd the Gentry as well as the Common People, with Principles oppoſite unto the <hi>Scotch</hi> Church Government, and moſt conform to the Rule ſettled by the firſt Reformers, in <hi>Defence</hi> of their Separation from <hi>Rome.</hi> And whoever will conſider what the Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liament did in <hi>Calling,</hi> and <hi>Directing</hi> their <hi>Synod,</hi> and in <hi>Approving</hi> and <hi>Rejecting</hi> what was Preſented to them by the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly, will ſee reaſon enough to conclude I am in the Right. For,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="subsection">
                  <p n="1">§.6. 1. This Synod was not called ei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther in the <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> or <hi>Claſſical</hi> way, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> obſerves, but the Parliament, as if Reſolv'd to take the <hi>Engliſh Presbyte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians</hi> for their Conduct, choſe the Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly themſelves. <q rend="inline">The Parliament (ſaith
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:66396:22"/> Mr. <hi>Baxter, ubi ſeq.</hi>) not intending to call an <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> which ſhould pretend a <hi>Divine Right,</hi> to make <hi>Obliging Laws,</hi> or <hi>Canons</hi> to bind their Brethren, but an <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Council,</hi> to be <hi>Adviſers</hi> to themſelves, did think they beſt knew who were the fitteſt to give them <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice,</hi> and therefore choſe them all them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelve.</q> Thus touching their <hi>Calling,</hi> which was moſt Remote from the <hi>Scotch-Claſſical</hi> way, and conform to the <hi>Engliſh-Presbyterian</hi> Principles, who are only for <hi>Perſwaſive Synods.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="subsection">
                  <p n="2">§.7. 2. This Aſſembly when thus cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led, could not proceed by virtue of any Inherent Power in themſelves, but in all their Debates were confined by the Parlia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment; ſo Mr. <hi>B.</hi> 
                     <q rend="inline">This Aſſembly was confined by <hi>Parliament,</hi> to Debate <hi>only</hi> ſuch things as they <hi>Propoſed</hi> to them. And many <hi>Lords</hi> and <hi>Commons</hi> were joyned in <hi>Commiſſion</hi> with them, <hi>to ſee, that they did not go beyond their Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</hi>
                     </q> So far was this Synod from being formed according to the <hi>Claſſical Model.</hi> Whence I infer,</p>
                  <pb n="35" facs="tcp:66396:22"/>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="subsection">
                  <p n="3">§.8. 3. That one Reaſon, why the Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſembly never adventur'd upon the ſettling the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of their Government, was becauſe the Parliament would never endure it. I ſay, that this is one Reaſon; for they had another which moved them to wave the <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> namely, their getting the greater Advantage againſt their Diſſenting Brethren, by putting 'em on the Proof of divers other General Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſitions, as neceſſary to evince, that the <hi>Presbyterial</hi> Government over many Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations <hi>might not be;</hi> Whereas, if the <hi>Aſſembly</hi> had Aſſerted the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of the Claſſical Government, or that it <hi>ra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther ſhould be,</hi> the Debate might have much ſooner come to an Iſſue; but their putting it only on a <hi>[may be,]</hi> left it in ſuch Ambiguous and Incomprehenſive Terms, as to neceſſitate their Opponents to thoſe <hi>Delays,</hi> that were in this Debate.</p>
                  <p>But as this was one Reaſon, ſo the <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>liaments</hi> being againſt the <hi>[must be,]</hi> had ſome Influence on the Aſſembly, and greatly Diſtreſſed them. And that the Parliament was againſt their <hi>Divine Right,</hi> is manifeſt from their Rejecting what did in the leaſt look that way, as it's related in the <hi>Preface</hi> to the <hi>Savoy-Confeſſion,</hi> where
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:66396:23"/>
'tis thus. <q rend="inline">The Honourable Houſes of Parliament thought it not convenient to have Matters of <hi>Diſcipline,</hi> and <hi>Church-Government</hi> put into a <hi>Confeſſion of Faith,</hi> eſpecially ſuch Particulars thereof as then were, and ſtill are Controverted and and under Diſpute by Men Orthodox and ſound in Faith. The 30th Chap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter therefore of that <hi>Confeſſion,</hi> as it was preſented to them by the <hi>Aſſembly,</hi> which is of <hi>Church Cenſures;</hi> as alſo <hi>Cap.</hi> 31. of <hi>Synods,</hi> and <hi>Councils,</hi> by <hi>whom</hi> to be <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led,</hi> of what <hi>Force</hi> in their <hi>Decrees</hi> and <hi>Determinations.</hi> — Theſe were ſuch <hi>Doubtful</hi> Aſſertions, and ſo Unſuitable to a <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of <hi>Faith,</hi> as the Honoura<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Houſes in their Great Wiſdom thought fit to lay them aſide.</q> So mani<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſt it is that the Parliament would never allow of the Church Government accord<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to the <hi>Scotch Modell,</hi> nor ſuffer any thing to look like their Synods having an <hi>Obliging</hi> Power over their Brethren; and conſidering the State of Affairs in that jun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cture, nothing but a Conviction, that the <hi>Engliſh Presbytery</hi> was more agreeable to the Scripture Rule, than the <hi>Claſſical,</hi> could have hindered their Complyance with the <hi>Scots</hi> in this Matter. It is alſo further to be obſerved,</p>
                  <pb n="37" facs="tcp:66396:23"/>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="subsection">
                  <p n="4">§.9. 4. That the Author of certain Conſiderations tending to Peace amongſt <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> Printed by <hi>Parkhurst, Anno</hi> 1674, doth expreſs himſelf thus, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="inline">The late <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Aſſembly, if you will have it <hi>called ſo,</hi> DIFFERED MUCH FROM THE ASSEMBLIES OF THE CHURCH of <hi>Scotland.</hi> They at <hi>Weſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>minſter</hi> (ſaith <hi>Heylin</hi>) Attribute <hi>Power</hi> to the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate,</hi> not only of <hi>cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Synods,</hi> and <hi>Church Aſſemblies,</hi> but alſo of being <hi>Preſent</hi> at <hi>them,</hi> and to Provide, that whatever is therein con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cluded, be done agreeably to the Mind, and Will of God. As to the <hi>Matter</hi> of <hi>Church-Government,</hi> the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of their <hi>Presbyteries</hi> — not a Word deli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered. Beſides, their <hi>National-Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies</hi> were to be <hi>Subordinate</hi> to the Power of the <hi>Parliament,</hi> — by the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of the 14th of <hi>March,</hi> which makes it <hi>quite</hi> ANOTHER THING <hi>from the</hi> SCOT<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TISH PRESBYTERIES, <hi>and other Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies of the</hi> KIRK, which hold themſelves to be SUPREME, and UNACCOUNTABLE in THEIR ACTINGS, <hi>without</hi> reſpect to the KING, the PARLIAMENT, and the <hi>Courts</hi> of <hi>Juſtice.</hi>
                     </q> So <hi>Heylin,</hi> in his <hi>Hi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtory of Presbyt.</hi> p. 476. So that tho the
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:66396:24"/> 
                     <hi>Scotch</hi> and <hi>Claſſical-Presbyterians</hi> laboured hard to ſet up their Government, yet could they not do it. Something of the <hi>Shadow</hi> of it they had, but not the Thing, and what they had, gave not ſatisfaction to the <hi>London Presbyterians.</hi> For,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="subsection">
                  <p n="5">§.10. 5. The <hi>Presbyterians</hi> of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince</hi> of <hi>London,</hi> conſidering the <hi>Church-Government</hi> Eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Ordinance</hi> of <hi>March</hi> 14. 1645, did, in their <hi>Conſide<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rations,</hi> and <hi>Cautions</hi> from <hi>Sion-Colledge, June,</hi> 19. 1646. declare, <q rend="inline">That there is not a <hi>Compleat Rule</hi> of <hi>theſe</hi> ORDINAN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CES: — That there are many <hi>Neceſſary</hi> things, NOT YET ESTABLISHED; and <hi>ſome things</hi> WHEREIN <hi>their Conſciences are</hi> NOT SO FULLY SATISFIED.</q> And at this time they Publiſhed in the ſame Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per, <q rend="inline">Their <hi>Joynt Reſolution</hi> to Practiſe in <hi>all things</hi> according to the <hi>Rule of the Word,</hi> and according to theſe Ordinan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, SO FAR AS THEY CONCEIVE THEM CORRESPONDENT TO IT.</q> Beſides,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="subsection">
                  <p n="6">S.11. 6. That Part of the Aſſemblies Confeſſion, which gave moſt <hi>Countenance</hi> to the <hi>Claſſical</hi> way, as it was Rejected by the Parliament, ſo was it haſtily Publiſhed from the <hi>Scotch</hi> Copy, where it had an
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:66396:24"/> Approbation; and ſuch is the Integrity of Zealots for the Claſſical Government, as to conceal the Approved Copy from the World, and Publiſh what never had an <hi>Imprimatur</hi> from that Government, which called the Aſſembly.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.12. Theſe Conſiderations may con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vince the Impartial Reader, that how much ſoever the <hi>Engliſh Presbytery</hi> took in this Nation from the Beginning of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formation, yet the <hi>Claſſical</hi> way would not go down either with the Gentry or Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon People; tho Epiſcopacy was laid a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſide, and <hi>Scottiſh</hi> Influences very power<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful, yet could not the Parliament be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed with to Eſtabliſh the <hi>Claſſical</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, and that their having ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>what like it, was enough to frighten the Sober People of <hi>England</hi> from a Cloſure with it. For,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.13. Tho in many Places the Miniſters were for it, yet as Dr. <hi>Du-Moulin,</hi> 
                     <q rend="inline">When the <hi>Presbyterian Government</hi> came to the <hi>Execution</hi> and <hi>Practice,</hi> there was not <hi>one</hi> of ten Thouſand of the People, that wuld ſubmit unto it. — And one of the Miniſters, who was the <hi>moſt Eminent,</hi> confeſſed to me, that being Paſtor of the
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:66396:25"/> Greateſt Pariſh, in <hi>London,</hi> he was ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver able to eſtabliſh in it a <hi>Conſiſtory,</hi> nor find any that would be of it, but a <hi>Pitiful Scotch Taylor.</hi>
                     </q> Vid. <hi>Confor. of the Inde<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendent Government, with that of the Primi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive,</hi> p. 36.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.14. The <hi>Cheſhire</hi> Miniſters in their Atteſtation to the Teſtimony of the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verend Brethren of the <hi>Province</hi> of <hi>Lon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>don,</hi> expreſs their <hi>Grief,</hi> becauſe ſo much of the <hi>Claſſical Presbytery</hi> as was Eſtabli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhed, prevailed ſo little in moſt Places, and impute the true Reaſons of it, <q rend="inline">Partly to the Mis-repreſentations of it to thoſe that ſhould ſubmit unto it; For to ſome it is (ſay they) rendered FORMIDABLE, as if it were MORE OPPRESSIVE <hi>than ever the Prelacy was;</hi> to others DESPI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>CABLE, for want of a <hi>Competent Power</hi> to proceed to <hi>Effectual</hi> Reformation of Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fenders:</q> That is, the Parliament annex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed no Penalties to be Inflicted on them, who could not in Conſcience conform to this National-Church-Conſtitution. More<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>over,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.15. There were amongſt the Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters a conſiderable Number, who enter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed into <hi>Aſſociations,</hi> and ſet up another
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:66396:25"/> ſort of Government, comprehending the <hi>Moderate Epiſcopal,</hi> and the <hi>Independents,</hi> upon the Principles maintain'd by the <hi>En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gliſh Presbyterians.</hi> For Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who was an <hi>Engliſh Presbyterian,</hi> was the Great Promoter of it; who freely declared, he could not agree with the Aſſembly in eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Point of Government (<hi>ubi ſup. P.</hi> 73.) and in <hi>P.</hi> 97. he mentions the Progreſs made of their Aſſociating Deſign.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.16. Thus great Endeavours were, during the time the Aſſembly ſate, for the bringing in the <hi>Claſſical</hi> Church Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, but 'twas ſo contrary to the <hi>Genius</hi> of the Nation, that no ſort, neither the Magiſtrate nor People, could be entirely for it, nor could the Shadow of it find ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptance amongſt us, the Sober Party, who Diſſented from the <hi>Dioceſans,</hi> being for the moſt part <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> and <hi>Congregationaliſts.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="section">
               <pb n="42" facs="tcp:66396:26"/>
               <head>SECT IV.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The <hi>ENGLISH PRESBYTERY</hi> after the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtauration of <hi>Charles II.</hi> prevail'd again, and ſo continued till the late <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>menced. Theſe things ſhewn out of the Writings of Dr. <hi>Collings,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Bax<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter.</hi>
                  </p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.1. WHen <hi>Charles</hi> II. was Reſtored, ſoon after the <hi>Presbyterians</hi> were caſt out, and the <hi>Epiſcopal</hi> put into their Places, whereupon the <hi>Nonconfor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſts,</hi> who were not of the <hi>Independent</hi> way, did ſoon, by their Practice, and the ſeveral Books written in Defence of their <hi>Nonconformity,</hi> convince their cloſeſt Ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſervers, that they were for thoſe Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples, which the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians</hi> had from time to time Aſſerted. And that thus much may with the greateſt Clear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, and to the moſt ſatisfaction be evin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced, I will refer to what Dr. <hi>Collings,</hi> and Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> have offered on this Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="subsection">
                  <p n="1">§.2. 1. Dr. <hi>Collings,</hi> who laboured much, and wrote well in the Controverſie about Church-Government, gives an Account
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:66396:26"/> of the <hi>main Opinions</hi> of thoſe Miniſters, and People in <hi>England,</hi> who go under the Name of <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> and calls his Book ENGLISH PRESBYTERY.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="subsection">
                  <p n="2">§.3. 2. In the Account he gives of their Opinions, he tells us, That they were for a <hi>Catholick Church Viſible,</hi> which the Old <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians</hi> would never own; but the it muſt be obſerv'd, that he doth not repreſent them as Aſſerters of a Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church Viſible, form'd into <hi>one Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vern'd Society,</hi> or <hi>an Organick Body.</hi> For he carefully appropriates the <hi>Governing</hi> Power to <hi>fixed ſingle Congregations,</hi> in which the <hi>Ruling Officers</hi> may have the Knowledge of every Member under his Care — His Words are, <q rend="inline">They Believe, that Chriſt hath Appropriated <hi>Miniſters</hi> of the Goſpel to this Viſible Church, who may Preach <hi>the Goſpel,</hi> and <hi>Baptize</hi> in any Parts of it, but CAN ONLY <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi> an <hi>ordinary Juriſdiction,</hi> in thoſe particular Parts of it, over which God hath given them a particular <hi>Overſight</hi> as <hi>Paſtors</hi> and <hi>Teachers. The Exerciſe of Acts</hi> of <hi>Juriſdiction,</hi> REQUIRING A PAR<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICULAR KNOWLEDGE of PERSONS O<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>PINIONS, KNOWLEDGE, and CONVER<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>SATION, which no ſingle Perſon can
<pb n="44" facs="tcp:66396:27"/> have as to <hi>all</hi> the Members of the <hi>Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Church,</hi>
                     </q> P. 6. §. 4. and in the ſame Page, § 6. 'tis added, <q rend="inline">They Believe Perſons thus <hi>ſet apart,</hi> (as in a forego<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>going Paragraph) to the Miniſtry, are fully Authorized to Preach the Goſpel, and to <hi>Baptize</hi> in any Place, where they are called to it, AND TO ADMINISTER THE LORD'S SUPPER, <hi>when they ſhall be</hi> FIXED IN ANY CONGREGATION, <hi>that they may Adminiſter it</hi> knowingly to Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons, <hi>that are able to diſcern the Lord's Body</hi> — and to EXERCISE ACTS OF JU<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>RISDICTION in THEIR FIXED CONGRE<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>GATION.</q> And <hi>P.</hi> 10. §. 2. <q rend="inline">An Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monition, which is a <hi>Church Cenſure,</hi> is the <hi>Act</hi> of the <hi>whole Congregation,</hi> or the officers of it, as well in the <hi>Name of Christ,</hi> as IN THEIR NAMES, ſhewing a Perſon Offending, his Errour from the Word of God, and Exhorting and Warning him to Reform. This they ſay, may be often Repeated. — 4. <hi>Excom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>muniation</hi> being the Higheſt Cenſure, they Believe, ought not to be Denoun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ced by <hi>any Perſons,</hi> but thoſe whom God's Word hath appointed thereunto. — The Perſons Decreating it, muſt be the <hi>Church,</hi> by its <hi>Officr,</hi> or <hi>Officers,</hi> (they agreeing thereunto—)</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="45" facs="tcp:66396:27"/>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="subsection">
                  <p n="3">§.4. 3. The <hi>Doctor,</hi> in theſe <hi>Paragraphs,</hi> as he truly Repreſents the <hi>Engliſh Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terians</hi> to be of Opinion, that Chriſt's Mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>niſters may <hi>Preach</hi> and <hi>Baptize,</hi> whenever in the Viſible Church they are called ſo: He adds, That they ſay, the <hi>Exerciſe</hi> of <hi>Juriſdiction</hi> belongs to the <hi>Miniſter,</hi> as <hi>he is fixed to a Congregation;</hi> that he is to <hi>Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moniſh</hi> Eccleſiaſtically in <hi>Chriſt's</hi> and the <hi>Churches Names;</hi> that the Perſons decree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to Excommunicate, muſt be the <hi>Church,</hi> by the Officer, or Officers; allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wing unto the <hi>Chriſtian Magiſtrate</hi> more Power in theſe Matters than <hi>Claſſical Presbyterians,</hi> as in <hi>P.</hi> 8, 9, and ſo far from making the Catholick Church Viſible, a <hi>Governed Society,</hi> or <hi>Organnick Body,</hi> that you ſee they Appropriate the Power of Juriſdiction unto a fixed a Congregation, without mentioning a Subordination of <hi>Claſſical,</hi> or <hi>Provincial Aſſemblies</hi> of the Ruling Officers, unto a National, or other Greater Synods. But,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="subsection">
                  <p n="1">§.5. 1. The Learned Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> who about the Nature and Conſtitution of Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches, hath been more Elabo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rate, and Convincing than moſt, in De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſending their <hi>Non-conformity</hi> unto the
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:66396:28"/> Church of <hi>England,</hi> doth moſt exactly deſcribe the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> fetch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing his Arguments from the Inconſiſtency there is between the <hi>Dioceſan Government,</hi> and the <hi>Specific</hi> Nature of Chriſt's <hi>Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuted Churches, Miniſtry,</hi> and <hi>Diſcipline.</hi> And,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="subsection">
                  <p n="2">§.6. 2. That he may the more clearly ſhew where the <hi>Strength</hi> of his Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments doth lie, he diſtinguiſheth between <hi>particular</hi> Inſtituted <hi>Churches,</hi> and the <hi>Catholick Church Viſible;</hi> affirming, that they are <hi>Specifically Diſtinct</hi> from each o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, upon the account of the <hi>different ſorts</hi> of <hi>Communion,</hi> that are had in a <hi>Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular,</hi> and in the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church. For, ſaith he,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="subsection">
                  <p n="3">§.7. 3. <hi>Communion,</hi> which is the Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiating <hi>End</hi> of theſe Societies, is twofold, The <hi>One</hi> ſort is in the ſame <hi>Species,</hi> or <hi>kind</hi> of <hi>Worſhip</hi> only; and the <hi>other,</hi> in the ſame <hi>Individual Acts of</hi> Worſhip: Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ding, that the Communion, which is in the ſame <hi>kind</hi> of Worſhip only, may be between them, who are at the greateſt diſtance from each other, and conſequent<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly with every Member of the Catholick Church Viſible, which therefore he cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth
<pb n="47" facs="tcp:66396:28"/> 
                     <hi>Catholick Communion,</hi> and ſeeing it can be only in <hi>kind,</hi> it cannot be more <hi>viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble,</hi> as <hi>ſuch</hi> than the <hi>Species</hi> of <hi>things are.</hi> But <hi>Communion,</hi> in the <hi>ſame Individual Acts</hi> of Worſhip, is by joyning in the ſame Ordinances of the <hi>Word, Prayer,</hi> and <hi>Lord's Supper,</hi> and they, who have Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion with each other, in this way, muſt meet in the ſame <hi>Place,</hi> at one and <hi>the ſame time,</hi> and 'tis therefore called <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonal-Preſential,</hi> or Local Communion, which is therefore <hi>Proper,</hi> and <hi>Adaequate</hi> to a particular Congregational-Church. This is a thing that muſt be Inculcated, <hi>viz. Communion</hi> in the ſame Individual Acts, can be had only in a ſingle Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gation, becauſe <hi>there alone</hi> they can actu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally joyn in the ſame Worſhip; whence it neceſſarily follows,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="subsection">
                  <p n="4">§.8. 4. That that Communion which is ſtretched beyond the Bounds of one ſingle Congregation, being only in the <hi>ſame kind</hi> of Worſhip, is of the <hi>ſame ſort</hi> with <hi>Catholick</hi> Communion. And ſeeing the Members of a <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> or <hi>Claſſical</hi> Church can have no other Communion with each other than what is <hi>Catholick,</hi> they want that Communion, which is Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential unto thoſe particular Churches
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:66396:29"/> which are of <hi>Divine Inſtitution,</hi> and ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cifically diſtinguiſhed from the <hi>Catholick</hi> Church. And on the other Hand, the Aſſerting <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> or <hi>Claſſical</hi> to be par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches of the <hi>Lowest Rank</hi> and <hi>Order,</hi> is <hi>quantum in ſe,</hi> a deſtroying Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſh, or <hi>Congregational Churches;</hi> and as ſtretching particular Churches to a larger <hi>Extent,</hi> is to make the <hi>Ends</hi> of their <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtitution impoſſible</hi> to be attained: As <hi>Mr. Alſop,</hi> in his <hi>Miſch. of Impoſ.</hi> 
                     <q rend="inline">It is very <hi>Lawful</hi> to build a <hi>Ship,</hi> or a <hi>Man of War</hi> as big as two or three <hi>Yachts,</hi> which may do better Service; but it's <hi>folly</hi> to make <hi>one</hi> that would reach from <hi>Calais</hi> to <hi>Dover,</hi> which muſt lie like a <hi>Log</hi> un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>meet for Sailing, and the Ends for which <hi>all Ships are Built.</hi>
                     </q> Which he mentions to ſhew, that the extending a particular Church beyond the Bounds of a ſingle Congregation, doth fruſtrate the <hi>End</hi> of its Inſtitution; or, as Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi> has it, <hi>makes</hi> the Impoſſibility <hi>of Chriſt's Diſcipline in our Churches undeniable.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="subsection">
                  <p n="5">§.9. 5. This Point being with much earneſtneſs ſtated by this Learned Perſon, he declares in the <hi>Narrative he wrote of his own Life, P.</hi> 339. "That one Charge, which the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> brought againſt
<pb n="49" facs="tcp:66396:29"/> our Prelacy is, <q rend="inline">That it deſtroyeth the <hi>Species,</hi> or <hi>Form</hi> of <hi>Particular Churches,</hi> Inſtituted by Chriſt. The Churches Inſtituted by Chriſt, are [<hi>Holy Socie<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties, Aſſociated for</hi> PERSONAL <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> under <hi>their Particular Pastors.</hi>]</q> But all ſuch Societies are Deſtroyed by the <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>oceſan</hi> Frame. — <hi>Ergo,</hi> 
                     <q rend="inline">It is deſtructive of the <hi>Form</hi> of Particular Churches In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted by Chriſt. They [<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Nonconformiſts,</hi>] diſtinguiſh between [<hi>Perſonal, Local</hi> Communion of Saints by Paſtors, and their Flocks] and [<hi>Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion of Heat only</hi>—] we have Heart-Communion with all the Catholick Church throughout the World — But [a <hi>Holy Communion of Souls,</hi> or <hi>Indivi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dual Perſons,</hi> as Members of the ſame Particular Church, for Publick Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip, and a Holy Life] is ESPECIALLY diſtinct from the former, as is apparent by the <hi>Diſtinct End:</hi> 2. The Diſtinct <hi>Manner</hi> of Communion; yea, and the <hi>Matter</hi> of it. And, in his <hi>Treatiſe of Epiſcopacy,</hi> more fully.</q> 
                     <q rend="inline">We cannot Subſcribe to that Form of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment as <hi>God,</hi> or <hi>Lawful,</hi> which in its Nature Excludeth or Deſtroyeth <hi>the ver Specifical Nature of the Particular Churches, which were Inſtituted by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:66396:30"/> Ghoſt, and ſettled in the Primitive Times</hi>—</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="inline">
                        <hi>But ſuch we take the preſent Dioceſan Form to be.</hi> Ergo,</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="inline">The <hi>Major</hi> will be denied by very few that we have to do with. — The <hi>Minor</hi> I thus prove.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="inline">
                        <hi>The</hi> Species <hi>of a Particular Church, which the Holy Ghost did Inſtitute,</hi> was [One <hi>Society of</hi> Chriſtians <hi>united under one or more Biſhops, for</hi> PERSONAL COMMUNION<gap reason="illegible" resp="#OXF" extent="1+ letters">
                           <desc>•…</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <hi>in Publick Worſhip, and Holy Living.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="inline">
                        <hi>The Dioceſan</hi> Engliſh <hi>Frame is</hi> [<hi>De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtructive of,</hi> or] <hi>Inconſiſtent with the Spe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cies of a Particular Church.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="inline">Ergo, <hi>The Dioceſan</hi> Engliſh <hi>Frame is Inconſiſtent with (or Deſtructive of) the Species of the Holy Ghoſt's Inſtitution.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="inline">In the <hi>Major,</hi> 1. By <hi>[Biſhops]</hi> I mean Sacred Miniſters, Authorized by Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Appointment, to be the STATED Guides of the Church, by Doctrine, Worſhip, and Diſcipline.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>By <hi>[Perſonal Communion]</hi> I mean, <q rend="inline">That the ſaid Churches were no more nume<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rous than our <hi>Engliſh</hi> Pariſhes, nor had more Aſſemblies; or no more than could have the ſame <hi>Perſonal Communion;</hi> and that there were never any Churches,
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:66396:30"/> 
                        <hi>Infimae vel primae Speciei,</hi> which conſiſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed of many ſuch Stated Aſſemblies. I ſhall therefore now Prove, That the Churches of the Holy Ghoſt's Inſtituti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, were no more Numerous, or were ſuch <hi>Single Congregations.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <q rend="inline">1. From the <hi>Holy Scriptures.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <q rend="inline">2. From the <hi>Confeſſion</hi> of the <hi>Dio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſans.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="3">
                     <q rend="inline">3. From the <hi>Teſtimony</hi> of <hi>Antiquity.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <q rend="inline">All proving fully, That the Ancient Epiſcopal Churches, were but <hi>ſuch ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gle Societies,</hi> or <hi>Congregations,</hi> as I have deſcribed.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="subsection">
                  <p n="6">§.10. 6. What Mr. <hi>B.</hi> here affirms, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpects chiefly the <hi>Communion</hi> of the <hi>Church,</hi> and upon this account he doth from the <hi>Specifical</hi> Difference there is between <hi>Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick,</hi> and <hi>Particular Church Communion;</hi> and from the Inconſiſtence there is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> and <hi>Pariſh,</hi> or <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional</hi> Churches; and the Deſtructive Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture of the Dioceſan Government, as 'tis framed to deſtroy <hi>Congregational Churches;</hi> from theſe Topicks, he brings thoſe <hi>Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments,</hi> by which he defends our <hi>Non<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>conformity</hi> to the Church of <hi>England,</hi> which he could never have done, were he not full well aſſured, that the <hi>Nonconformiſts</hi> ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:66396:31"/> held Particular Churches to be <hi>Congregational.</hi> And,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="subsection">
                  <p n="7">§.11. 7. That he was ſatisfied his Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guments were as much againſt <hi>Claſſical,</hi> as they were againſt <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Churches, evi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dently appears by what he hath in his <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy, Part</hi> 1. <hi>C.</hi> 7. <hi>P.</hi> 120. when he ſaith, <q rend="inline">That by a <hi>Dioceſan</hi> Church, WE mean all the <hi>Chriſtians</hi> within that <hi>Circuit,</hi> who have but one Biſhop over them, tho' they be of MA<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>NY PARISH CHURCHES, yea FEW PRES<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>BYTERIANS take the Word ſo Narrow as this. For, (I think) too <hi>many of them</hi> do with <hi>Rutherford</hi> Diſtinguiſh between a <hi>Worſhipping Church,</hi> and a <hi>Governing Church,</hi> (and SADLING THE HORSE FOR PRELACY TO MOUNT ON) do Affirm, that many (about Twelve uſually) of theſe <hi>Worſhiping</hi> Churches, like our Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſhes) may make but one <hi>Governed,</hi> or <hi>Presbyterial</hi> Church.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.12. What more <hi>directly</hi> belongs to the <hi>Government</hi> of the Church, we ſhall conſider, if God will, elſewhere; and will only Note in this place, That whoever will conſult Mr. <hi>Baxter</hi>'s <hi>Treatiſe</hi> of <hi>Epiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>copacy,</hi> and what he ſaith of the <hi>Miniſtry</hi>
                     <pb n="53" facs="tcp:66396:31"/> and <hi>Diſcipline</hi> of Chriſt's Inſtituted Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, will find that the <hi>Engliſh Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> whom he deſcribes, were as much againſt the <hi>Claſſical Presbytery,</hi> as the <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregationaliſts</hi> are. We will in the next propoſe the Sentiments of thoſe <hi>Engliſh Presbyterians,</hi> who entered into an Union with their <hi>Congregational Brethren.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="section">
               <head>SECT. V.</head>
               <argument>
                  <p>The <hi>Difference</hi> between the <hi>Claſſical Pres<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>byterian,</hi> and the <hi>Congregationaliſt</hi> ſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted. The <hi>Deſign</hi> of the <hi>late Union,</hi> and the <hi>Principles,</hi> upon which 'twas founded, conſiſtent with the <hi>Eſtabliſhed National Chuch Form,</hi> and ſuch <hi>as</hi> Juſtifie the <hi>Separation</hi> of the <hi>Firſt Reformers</hi> from <hi>Rome.</hi> The Claſſical odel Deſtructive of them, and therefore Rejected.</p>
               </argument>
               <div n="1" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.1. THAT it may be the more eaſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly underſtood what <hi>Principles</hi> the <hi>Presbyterians,</hi> who were Men of Senſe and Integrity, muſt be ſuppoſed to be of, when they <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited</hi> with their <hi>Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Brethren;</hi> I will give an Impartial State of the Controverſie about the <hi>Nature</hi> and <hi>Power</hi> of Inſtituted Churches, as diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cuſs'd by them, who were for the <hi>Claſſical</hi>
                     <pb n="54" facs="tcp:66396:32"/> Church Government, and by the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents forty</hi> or <hi>fifty</hi> Years ago.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.2. This <hi>Controverſie,</hi> as to that part of it which concerns my preſent Purpoſe, may be reduced to theſe Heads.</p>
                  <p n="1">1. Whether there be a <hi>Catholick-Viſible-Political-Church?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">2. Whether there be a <hi>Particular Church Eſſential <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>norganiz'd,</hi> veſted <hi>with a Power to chooſe their own Officers?</hi> Or, <hi>An Eccleſia Inſtitute ſit Genus? An Integrum?</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.3. In the Writings of <hi>Cawdrey, Hud<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, Hooker, Stone, Allen, Sheppard,</hi> and the Diſſenting Brethren of the <hi>Weſtminſter</hi> Aſſembly, there being an Impartial State of this Controverſie, I will, out of their Writings, ſet it in as clear a Light as I can.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="subsection">
                  <p n="1">§.4. 1. The Learned Mr. <hi>Cawdrey,</hi> who agreeth in Opinion with the Judicious Mr. <hi>Hudſon,</hi> and the <hi>London</hi> Miniſters in their <hi>Jus Divinum,</hi> doth, in his <hi>Vindiciae Vindiciarum,</hi> and <hi>Review</hi> of Mr. <hi>Hooker</hi>'s <hi>Survey,</hi> declare not only for a <hi>Viſible Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church,</hi> but <q rend="inline">That this <hi>Viſible Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church</hi> may, in a fair and candid Senſe, be ſaid to be POLITICAL, and
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:66396:32"/> that the Notion of CHURCH-ESSENTIAL, or HOMOGENOUS, is but the <hi>Modus,</hi> or State of a Church, applicable both to the whole Chuch, and every compleat Congregation, conſiſting of <hi>Viſible Saints</hi> and <hi>Officers</hi> — But, it is not poſſible there ſhould be an <hi>Eſſential-Church</hi> exi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſting without <hi>Officers</hi> — If we would ſpeak exactly, neither a <hi>Claſſis</hi> of Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers Aſſembled, nor a Company of Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Saints combined, can <hi>properly</hi> be cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led a <hi>Church.</hi> They [<hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Indepen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dents,</hi>] deny a <hi>Claſſis</hi> of Officers to be a Church; and <hi>We</hi> [who are for <hi>Claſſes,</hi>] deny a Company of Saints, combined without <hi>Officers</hi> to be a <hi>Church,</hi> being both of them but PARTS of a Church; part of the <hi>Matter</hi> of a Church, and therefore PROPERLY no Church. The Truth is, tho' both a <hi>Claſſis,</hi> and a Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pany of Saints combined without Offi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers, have by Cuſtom, obtained to be called Churches, yet PROPERLY they are but <hi>Parts</hi> or <hi>Members</hi> of the whole Church diverſly combined — But we add, If we will ſpeak exactly, a Particular Congregation conſiſting of <hi>Officers</hi> and <hi>Members,</hi> is not PROPERLY a <hi>Church,</hi> but a Member of the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Viſible</hi> POLITICAL <hi>Church</hi> — And,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:66396:33"/> if they, much more ſome <hi>Members</hi> of that <hi>Member;</hi> Viſible Saints, without Officers, are <hi>Improperly</hi> called a Church — Again, here lies one of the great Miſtakes in the <hi>Independent</hi> way, That <hi>they imagine a Church without, and before any Officers,</hi> and then give them Power to make <hi>Officers.</hi> — So far the Learned Mr. <hi>Cawdrey.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="subsection">
                  <p n="2">§.5. 2. The Judicious Mr. <hi>Hudſon,</hi> ſtates the Controverſie after the ſame man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner, but more elaborately, and with grea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Logical Exactneſs, and expreſly affirms the <hi>Catholick Church</hi> Viſible to be a <hi>Totum Integrale,</hi> or POLITICAL Society; to be a <hi>Corporation,</hi> or Body Politick, in which there is a <hi>Governing,</hi> and <hi>Governed Part.</hi> And on the Suppoſition, that the Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church Viſible is a <hi>Totum Integrale,</hi> 'twill unavoidably follow, as Learned Mr. <hi>Calamy</hi> hath happily expreſſed it in his <hi>Preface</hi> to Mr. <hi>Hudſon,</hi> that the <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional Government</hi> is not right. <q rend="inline">The Truth is (ſaith he) the Poſition there held forth, would utterly overthrow the <hi>Grounds</hi> and <hi>Pillars</hi> of the Congre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gational Government; for if there be a Catholick Church Viſible, and this Church be not only a <hi>Church Entitive,</hi>
                        <pb n="57" facs="tcp:66396:33"/> but a <hi>Church Organical,</hi> and a <hi>Totum In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrale,</hi> having all Church Powers <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually</hi> ſeated in the <hi>Officers</hi> of it, which they have Commiſſions from Chriſt to Exert, and put into Act upon a Lawful Call; and if particular Congregations are <hi>Integral</hi> Parts and Members of the <hi>Church Catholick,</hi> as the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Syna<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gogues were of the <hi>Jewiſh</hi> Church; and if the <hi>Miniſtry,</hi> Orders, and Cenſures were given by Chriſt, <hi>first</hi> to the Church Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Viſible, and <hi>ſecondarily</hi> to the Church Particular, then 'twill follow, that the particular Congregation is not the <hi>First Receptacle</hi> of Church <hi>Power;</hi> and that all Church Power is not <hi>Entire<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> and <hi>Independently</hi> in a particular Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation.</q> So far Mr. <hi>Calamy,</hi> to whom I add, That according to this Notion, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible Saints combined for Church Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion without Officers, are not a <hi>Church Eſſential,</hi> and <hi>have not a Power</hi> to chooſe Officers, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> For upon this Principle, it's manifeſt, yea 'tis owned, That to the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church Viſible, which is a <hi>Totum Integrale,</hi> or an <hi>Organized Body,</hi> a POLI<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>TICAL Church, the <hi>Adminiſtration</hi> and <hi>Immediate</hi> Participation of Government, and all other Ordinances are firſtly and immediately given; yea further, it muſt
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:66396:34"/> be granted, that particular Churches, whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther <hi>Congregational</hi> or <hi>Claſſical, Provincial</hi> or <hi>National,</hi> are not <hi>Properly</hi> Churches, but <hi>Integral Parts</hi> of the Catholick Viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble POLITICAL Church; that whoever is a Viſible Chriſtian, has an Immediate Right to all Ordinances; and that the Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lation of every <hi>Miniſter</hi> is <hi>firſtly</hi> and <hi>habi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tually</hi> unto the Catholick Church Viſible, and <hi>ſecondarily</hi> to this or that <hi>Particular</hi> Church, which is not <hi>Properly</hi> a Church; that where-ever any ſingle <hi>Chriſtian</hi> comes, he is a Member of the Particular Church in that Place, and has a Right to all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances, tho he never joyn'd himſelf to any; and whoever is ordained, he is a Paſtor of the Catholick Church, may Adminiſter all Ordinances, whither ſoever he comes, and Excommunicate Delinquents. Tho', for <hi>Order ſake,</hi> his Power is not exerciſed, yet the Power remains <hi>Entire</hi> in every Or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dained Miniſter, even in them who are called to take the Charge of any particular Church.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="subsection">
                  <p n="1">§.6. 1. On the other hand, the <hi>First Reformers</hi> of all Perſwaſions ſubverted this <hi>Notion</hi> in their Oppoſition unto the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> by denying ſuch a thing as a Viſible Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church, <hi>Sublato Fundamento tolli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:66396:34"/> opus.</hi> And they who now own, that the many Viſible <hi>Chriſtians,</hi> ſcattered through the World, may be called the <hi>Catholick Church Viſible,</hi> yet do ſtrenuouſly oppugn its being a <hi>Political</hi> Church. And theſe Congregationaliſts affirm the Church Catholick Viſible to be <hi>Totum <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſale, Genericum,</hi> or as they ſometimes expreſs it, a <hi>Totum Eſſentiale;</hi> that this <hi>Totum Gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ricum</hi> gives <hi>Eſſence</hi> unto its <hi>Species,</hi> or Parts, and is its Cauſe, and in order of Nature before its <hi>Species,</hi> as a <hi>Cauſe is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore its Effects,</hi> But then it muſt, (to prevent miſtake) be carefully obſerv'd, that by [Church Univerſal Viſible] they mean a Congregational, or a Particular <hi>Church Eſſential,</hi> which including the <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral Nature</hi> of a Church, they call <hi>Ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neral</hi> or <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſal;</hi> but ſuch as hath (where the Combination is) its <hi>Eſſentials</hi> exiſtent, antecedently to the Conſiderati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on of its being an <hi>Integrum,</hi> or a <hi>Body Po<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>litick,</hi> and as ſuch is dreſſed with a <hi>Power</hi> of <hi>chooſing</hi> its Officers, and of becoming thereby a <hi>Totum Integrale,</hi> or an <hi>Organick</hi> Body.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="7" type="subsection">
                  <p n="2">§.7. 2. <hi>Fit Matter</hi> Combined, before formed into an <hi>Organick Body,</hi> is, (with them) the <hi>Church Eſſential;</hi> the only im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:66396:35"/> Seat of Church Power; or, to expreſs it in the Words of Mr. <hi>Allen</hi> and Mr. <hi>Sheppard,</hi> (<hi>Def. of the Nine Propoſit.</hi> p. 88.) <q rend="inline">The true <hi>Form</hi> of all Church Societies, Inſtituted by Chriſt, to which he hath given the actual Adminiſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, and Immediate Participation of Church Government, and all other In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtituted Ordinances, as the <hi>Subject</hi> there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>of, is <hi>Congregational.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="8" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.8. Theſe two Reverend Brethren do not, (I confeſs) think themſelves obliged to encumber this Controverſie with thoſe <hi>Logical Niceties</hi> of a <hi>Totum Genericum,</hi> a <hi>Totum Integrale,</hi> yet do they hold, <q rend="inline">That the <hi>true State</hi> of this Controverſie lies here, concerning the NATURE, ORDER, and FORM of ſuch Viſible Societies, as Chriſt Jeſus, by Divine Inſtitution in the Goſpel, hath reduced his Viſible Members unto, for the Actual and <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediate</hi> Injoyment of all his Inſtituted Ordinances.</q> And the Chain of their Principles lies thus.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, There is a Particular Church <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential,</hi> which is <hi>Congregational;</hi> this Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregation is made up of Viſible Saints, who upon their Mutual Conſent and A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement to walk together according to
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:66396:35"/> Goſpel Rule, have an Immediate Right to <hi>Stated</hi> Communion in all the Special Ordinances of the Goſpel; that as they have Power to Combine together, as a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>foreſaid, ſo being combined, they have a Power of chooſing their own <hi>Officers,</hi> as being furniſhed with ſuch, have received Authority from Jeſus Chriſt to Exerciſe Government, and of enjoying all Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Worſhip within themſelves.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="9" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.9. Theſe then are the Points where<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in Mr. <hi>Cawdrey, Hudſon,</hi> and others, who were for the <hi>Claſſical</hi> Churches and Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, differed from the old <hi>Noncon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formiſts,</hi> and the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Congregationalist.</hi> For, the <hi>Eccleſiaſtical Presbyterians</hi> held the Catholick Church Viſible to be a <hi>Body Politick;</hi> the <hi>first Seat</hi> of all Ordinances, and that the Paſtor's Office was with Relation to the whole Catholick Church; that they might Ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miniſter all Ordinances of Worſhip and Diſcipline whereſoever they came. The Congregational <hi>Presbyterian,</hi> in oppoſition unto 'em, denied the Catholick Church Viſible to be a <hi>Body Politick,</hi> or <hi>Governed Society,</hi> that Viſible Saints combin'd for Communion in all Odinances, <hi>whilst with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out Officers,</hi> were a particular Church <hi>Eſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſential;</hi>
                     <pb n="62" facs="tcp:66396:36"/> tha theſe Churches had <hi>Power to chooſe their own Officers;</hi> and that the <hi>Ru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling Power</hi> of theſe <hi>Officers</hi> was confined within the Bounds of <hi>Congregational Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Churches.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="10" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.10. Well then let us in the next place compare theſe diſtinct Notions with the late <hi>Heads</hi> of <hi>Agreement,</hi> and ſee whether the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Brethren</hi> fell in with the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterian</hi> Principles in this <hi>Matter,</hi> or not?</p>
               </div>
               <div n="11" type="subsection">
                  <p n="1">§.11. 1. If we do but impartially ob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerve the <hi>Deſign</hi> of this <hi>Agreement,</hi> we ſhall find it to be nothing elſe than an <hi>Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>provement</hi> of our <hi>Liberty,</hi> in ſuch a way as may moſt <hi>effectually convince</hi> them of the <hi>Church</hi> of <hi>England,</hi> that nothing is more <hi>Remote</hi> from our Thoughts, than a ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>king the leaſt Incroachment upon, or in any wiſe an Intermedling with the <hi>Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church Form;</hi> and whereas the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational and <hi>Engliſh Presbyterian</hi> Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples are beſt adjuſted to this end, as well as moſt <hi>Conform</hi> to the Goſpel Rule, we took ſpecial care in drawing up the <hi>A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greement,</hi> to Aſſert, and Explain their Principles. And therefore, as we did in the <hi>Preface,</hi> and in the <hi>Title</hi> of the firſt
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:66396:36"/> Page, poſitively declare againſt <hi>Intermed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling</hi> with the <hi>National Church Form:</hi> So,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="12" type="subsection">
                  <p n="2">§.12. 2. We did expreſs our <hi>Diſlike</hi> of that Principle, on which either a <hi>Dioce<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſan,</hi> or <hi>Claſſical</hi> Church <hi>Government,</hi> is erected: For by the <hi>first Article</hi> in the <hi>first Section,</hi> the <hi>Catholick</hi> Churches being a <hi>Totum Integrale,</hi> a Society under an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal <hi>Polity</hi> or <hi>Government,</hi> is <hi>Diſclaimed</hi> in theſe Words, <hi>viz.</hi> 
                     <q rend="inline">But as for the No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of a Viſible Catholick Church, as it may ſignifie its having been collected into any <hi>Formed Society,</hi> under a <hi>Viſible Head</hi> on Earth; whether <hi>one Perſon ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gly,</hi> or many <hi>collectively,</hi> we, with the reſt of <hi>Proteſtants,</hi> do UNANIMOUSLY DISCLAIM IT.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="13" type="subsection">
                  <p n="3">§.13. 3. Agreeably hereunto, a particu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lar Church ESSENTIAL, with its <hi>Rights</hi> and Liberties, is <hi>Aſſerted,</hi> and <hi>Deſcribed,</hi> firſt more generally, <hi>Art.</hi> 2. <q rend="inline">We Agree, that particular Societies of Viſible Saints, who under Chriſt their Head are <hi>ſtated<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly</hi> joyn'd together for ORDINARY COM<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MUNION <hi>with one another</hi> in ALL THE <hi>Ordinances</hi> of Chriſt, are <hi>Particular Churches.</hi>
                     </q> That is to ſay, a Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of Viſible Saints, <hi>ſtatedly</hi> joyn'd toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:66396:37"/> for theſe Ends. So that here is a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Church Eſſential aſſerted, that this particular Church <hi>Eſſential</hi> is Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onal alſo cleared, and <hi>as ſuch</hi> agreed un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to; for it's ſaid, that they are <hi>ſtatedly</hi> joyn'd together for ORDINARY <hi>Communion with one another,</hi> in <hi>all the Ordinances of Christ, which cannot</hi> be but in <hi>one ſingle Congregation.</hi> But,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="14" type="subsection">
                  <p n="4">§.14. 4. There is ſpecial care taken to ſecure this Principle by declaring in the <hi>ſecond Article, That theſe Societies are to be owned by each other for Inſtituted Churches of Christ,</hi> than which nothing can be more plainly delivered, in oppoſition to the <hi>Claſſical</hi> Government.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="15" type="subsection">
                  <p n="5">§.15. 5. This particular Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church <hi>Eſſential,</hi> is more particularly deſcribed as to its <hi>Matter</hi> and <hi>Form, Art.</hi> 3. and 4. Beſides,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="16" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.16. The <hi>Right</hi> of this Church <hi>Eſſen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tial</hi> to chooſe its own Officers, is ſecured by <hi>Art.</hi> 6. <q rend="inline">That each Particular Church hath <hi>Right</hi> to <hi>chooſe their own Officers,</hi> and being furniſhed with ſuch as are duly Qualified and Ordained according to Goſpel Rule, HATH AUTHORITY <hi>from
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:66396:37"/> Jeſus Christ,</hi> for EXERCISING GOVERN<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>MENT, and of <hi>Enjoying</hi> ALL <hi>the Ordi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nances of Worſhip</hi> WITHIN IT SELF.</q> This then being the Turning Point be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween <hi>thoſe</hi> who are for a <hi>Catholick Church Government,</hi> and <hi>theſe,</hi> who are for a Par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular Congregational Government; I will be the more diſtinct in ſhowing what depends on a Right, or wrong ſtating it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="17" type="subsection">
                  <p n="1">§.17. 1. If this <hi>Article</hi> contains <hi>not</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> then indeed the Cauſe muſt be yielded to the <hi>Claſſical, Dioceſan, Provin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial, National, Patriarchal, and Papal Church Government.</hi> For, upon the ſame <hi>Reaſon</hi> the Government is ſtretched be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>yond a ſingle Congregational, to a <hi>Claſſical</hi> Church, it muſt be carried to the outmoſt Bounds of the <hi>Catholick,</hi> which is the <hi>Papal:</hi> For it is impoſſible to carry it to a <hi>Claſſical,</hi> or <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> upon any other Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon, than as it is a <hi>Larger part</hi> of the Ca<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tholick Church Polity, which ſtill muſt pay a Deference unto a Larger, until you come to a larger than that, and at laſt to the <hi>Largest</hi> of all, <hi>viz.</hi> the <hi>Papal;</hi> which is a Truth that hath been ſo fully cleared by Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> and is in its own Nature ſo very <hi>Plain</hi> and Obvious, that
<pb n="66" facs="tcp:66396:38"/> a ſmall Meaſure of Attention will help an ordinary Capacity to ſee into it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="18" type="subsection">
                  <p n="2">§.18. 2. But, if this Article, of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Brethren</hi> DOTH contain the <hi>Truth,</hi> and a particular <hi>Church Eſſential</hi> hath Power to chooſe its own Officers; and being furniſhed with ſuch, hath received Authority from Chriſt to exerciſe <hi>Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment,</hi> and enjoy all <hi>Ordinances of</hi> Wor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip <hi>within it ſelf,</hi> then it unavoidably fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows, that Congregational Churches are in a <hi>Proper Senſe</hi> Particular Churches; that all Church Power doth <hi>firſtly</hi> belong unto them; and that <hi>Claſſical, Provincial, Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional, Patriarchal,</hi> Churches are not <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perly Churches,</hi> nor have they a Power over Particular Congregational Churches. Be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſides,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="19" type="subsection">
                  <p n="3">§.19. 3. If the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Brethren,</hi> name<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, the <hi>Engliſh Presbyterian</hi> and <hi>Congregati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onalists,</hi> do herein Aſſert no more than they are Authorized to do by the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus, then the <hi>First Refor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mers</hi> in their <hi>Separation from</hi> ROME, <hi>and</hi> their ſetting up Churches of another ſort, than what were eſtabliſhed by the <hi>Pope,</hi> did no more than what they were em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>powered by <hi>Jeſus Christ</hi> himſelf <hi>to do,</hi> as
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:66396:38"/> will clearly appear by an Impartial Propo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſal of the Judgment of the Learned <hi>Gil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bertus Voetius, Meinardus Shottanus,</hi> and <hi>Carolus de Maetz,</hi> Divinity Profeſſors at <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>trecht,</hi> which upon ſuch Mighty Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>derations, as relate to the <hi>Vitals</hi> of the <hi>Reformation</hi> they gave, in the reſolving ſome Caſes propoſed unto them, on the Forming that <hi>Particular Church,</hi> of which one Mr. <hi>Park</hi> was choſen <hi>Paſtor,</hi> who hath ſaid enough to juſtifie what the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nited Brethren</hi> have Aſſerted about a <hi>Parti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cular Church</hi> ESSENTIAL, and the Power of chooſing her own Officers. Conſider then that the Queſtions propoſed were,</p>
                  <p n="1">
                     <q rend="inline">1. Whether ſuch <hi>Faithful Perſons,</hi> as without the Authority of any Eccleſia<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtical <hi>Society,</hi> either <hi>Claſſical,</hi> or <hi>Presby<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terial,</hi> by <hi>Combination</hi> forming them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves into a <hi>Society</hi> for Communion, in the Ordinances of the Goſpel, may be <hi>Acknowledged</hi> to be ESSENTIALLY a <hi>Church?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p n="2">
                     <q rend="inline">2. Whether <hi>this Church</hi> ESSENTIAL hath <hi>Power</hi> to chooſe a <hi>Paſtor?</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>To the firſt they anſwer, <q rend="inline">That it is, and may be ſaid to be <hi>Eſſentially</hi> a <hi>True Church of Christ,</hi> [<hi>Diſtinguenda est,</hi> (ſay they) <hi>Eccleſiae Particularis</hi> Eſſentia <hi>ab</hi> INTEGRITATE, <hi>&amp; Perfectione ejus</hi>
                        <pb n="68" facs="tcp:66396:39"/> ORGANICA, <hi>Voet. Pol. Eccleſ. Part.</hi> 1. <hi>Lib.</hi> 1. <hi>Cap.</hi> 3.] to wit, an <hi>External, Vi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſible,</hi> Inſtituted, Parochial, Particular Church.</q> Their <hi>fourth Reaſon</hi> for it is this. <q rend="inline">If the contrary Opinion ſhould be admitted, we cannot (ſay they) ſee what may be the Conſequences thereof, with reſpect to thoſe <hi>Difficult Controver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſies</hi> with the <hi>Papiſts,</hi> about the <hi>Perpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tual Succeſſion</hi> of the Churches ſome Years before <hi>Luther,</hi> about their <hi>Sepa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ration</hi> from <hi>Rome;</hi> about the firſt <hi>Ga<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thering</hi> and <hi>Conſtituting</hi> Reformed Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches; and <hi>calling of Miniſters</hi> before, with, at, and ſince the Reforma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="20" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.20. The Strength of what they offer on this Occaſion, lieth here; namely, in caſe Viſible Saints combin'd for Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion in the Ordinances of the Goſpel, have <hi>Power,</hi> by Virtue of Jeſus Chriſt's Inſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tution, to <hi>call</hi> and <hi>chooſe their own Officers:</hi> The firſt Reformers, in combining thus, and chooſing their own Officers, acted in purſuance of the <hi>Authority</hi> given 'em by Jeſus Chriſt, and are Juſtified. But had they not ſuch a <hi>Power,</hi> their Caſe is not ea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſily defended. Theſe Great Divines there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore in Anſwer to the ſecond <hi>Enquiry,</hi> af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firm,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:66396:39"/> 
                     <hi>That a Church</hi> Eſſential <hi>has a Power belonging unto it, to call a Paſtor.</hi> So that theſe Learned Men, have urged Argu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments ſufficient to juſtifie what the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Brethren</hi> have done, in defining a Church <hi>Eſſential,</hi> and in ſhewing how it becomes an <hi>Integral, Organical, Political</hi> Body: And what they have urged from the Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſideration of the Fatal Conſequences of the contrary Doctrine, with reſpect to the <hi>First Reformation,</hi> hath enough in it to ſatisfie any conſidering Mind about the Reaſons that have Influenced the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Brethren,</hi> to fix their Foot on this Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple about a Particular Church <hi>Eſſential,</hi> in the framing the Heads of their Agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment. Once more,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="21" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.21. As the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nited Brethren</hi> have Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſerted Particular Churches to be <hi>Congrega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tional,</hi> ſo it's evident, they have <hi>confined the Power of their Officers to their</hi> own Churches: For in the <hi>Section</hi> of <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion</hi> with <hi>other</hi> Churches, <hi>Art.</hi> 2. it is a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greed, <q rend="inline">That none of our Particular Churches ſhall be <hi>Subordinate</hi> to one a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nother; each being endow'd with <hi>Equa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity of Power</hi> from Jeſus Chriſt; and that none of the ſaid <hi>Particular</hi> Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, their <hi>Officer,</hi> or <hi>Officers,</hi> ſhall <hi>Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe</hi>
                        <pb n="70" facs="tcp:66396:40"/> any <hi>Power,</hi> or have <hi>any Superiority</hi> over any <hi>other Church,</hi> or <hi>their Officers.</hi>
                     </q> So clear it is, that this <hi>Article,</hi> by denying unto <hi>one Officer</hi> ſingly, and to <hi>many Officers collectively,</hi> any ſort of Power, or Superi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ority over one another, doth lay an im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pregnable Bar againſt the ſetting up of <hi>Claſſical, Provincial,</hi> or <hi>National</hi> Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>blies, inveſted with a Power to govern Congregational Churches. For, it muſt be acknowledged, that in forming the late <hi>Heads</hi> of <hi>Agreement,</hi> ſpecial care was taken to convince them of the Church of <hi>England,</hi> that there was no place for us to make the leaſt Incroachments on the Eſtabliſhed National Church Form; That the <hi>Mounds</hi> and Barriers we raiſed to keep all within the Confines of the <hi>Tolleration</hi> granted us, were ſuch, that no ſincere Approver of the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nion,</hi> can have any Hand in erecting any thing like a Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Church Form; and therefore can ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver be for Claſſical, Provincial or Natio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Aſſemblies of Miniſters: Their going about any ſuch thing, is a breaking down the ſtrongeſt Mounds, a violating the moſt Solemn Engagements, and a tearing up the very Foundation, on which the late Union was built, which can never be anſwered to our Countrey Brethren, nor to their
<pb n="71" facs="tcp:66396:40"/> own Conſciences, much leſs unto a Holy and Jealous God. For,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="22" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.22. By the <hi>Heads</hi> of <hi>Agreement, as</hi> all that Church Power we claim is confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned to Particular Congregational Chur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches, and a Superiority of Power denied to any one Officer or Officers of Churches; ſo <hi>Particular Churches</hi> were no further concern'd to give any account of their own Actings, beſide what the <hi>Civil Magiſtrate</hi> requires, but what on ſome ſpecial Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſions might be needful in a Brotherly way to Neighbour Congregations when deſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red, and 'twas for the removal of Scandals, or the rectifying Miſtakes. But for <hi>ſtated</hi> Claſſical, Provincial, or Natural Aſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles, and the coming under the Obligation of making a <hi>Diligent Obſervation,</hi> and a <hi>Faithful Report</hi> of the <hi>State</hi> of their Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregations, unto any of thoſe larger Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſemblies, there is not one Word in our <hi>Agreement.</hi> Nor, can any of our Num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber conſent that our Miniſters ſhould take upon 'em the Office of ſtated <hi>Inquiſitors,</hi> or <hi>Informers:</hi> For, as ſuch an <hi>Imploy</hi> is as likely to <hi>Ruine,</hi> as it is to ſerve its chiefeſt Contrivers, ſo it's <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nworthy</hi> of <hi>Men,</hi> in ſo Holy a Function, and contrary to that Work, Chriſt Jeſus has called his Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:66396:41"/> unto; which, lying in ſtrenuous En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours to further the Salvation of them committed to their care, cannot be faith<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully performed, but by keeping within the <hi>Pale</hi> of their <hi>Single Congregations.</hi> And ſeeing this is what is granted to us by the <hi>Toleration,</hi> to which we have hitherto <hi>confined</hi> our ſelves, we declare it to be our <hi>Firm Reſolution,</hi> always to do ſo; being as much <hi>Diſſatisfied</hi> with that <hi>Church-Form,</hi> which endangers the Eſtabliſhed Church, as any in that Church can be, For,</p>
               </div>
               <div n="23" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.23. That very <hi>Form</hi> of Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment, which alone can give juſt Ground of Suſpicion, is as <hi>Deſtructive</hi> of thoſe Churches we believe to be of <hi>Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vine Inſtitution,</hi> as it can be of the Eſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bliſhed Church <hi>Form.</hi> The <hi>Jure Divino Claſſical Government,</hi> that <hi>Rivals</hi> it with the <hi>Epiſcopal,</hi> doth as really deſtroy <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregational Churches,</hi> by making them but <hi>Parts</hi> of a <hi>Proper Church,</hi> as it would ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vert the <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> were it ſet up amongſt us. Yea, if we more cloſely look into this Matter, we ſhall find the <hi>Claſſical</hi> Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment more <hi>Hurtful</hi> to our Church way, than it can be to <hi>theirs,</hi> ſeeing it al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lows of <hi>Dioceſan,</hi> under the Name of <hi>Claſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſical,</hi>
                     <pb n="73" facs="tcp:66396:41"/> and ſtrikes only at their <hi>Rulers,</hi> and not at their <hi>Church-ſtate,</hi> whilſt it <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>n<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>churches</hi> all our <hi>Congregations,</hi> and Diveſts the <hi>Officers</hi> of that Power, which we think Chriſt has given them; and are therefore more <hi>Formidable</hi> unto, and <hi>Dreaded</hi> by <hi>us,</hi> than by the Church it ſelf; which Conſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deration will, we hope, ſatisfie our <hi>Supe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riours,</hi> and every thoughtful Perſon of the Church, That they are in <hi>no Danger from us.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="24" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.24. That they deſtroy our Church way, is farther evident, in that they bring every <hi>Paroch</hi> and <hi>Congregation</hi> under the Government of their <hi>Claſſical,</hi> and other Larger <hi>Aſſemblies,</hi> by the Obligation of a <hi>Divine Law;</hi> and that they may to their own greater Satisfaction, prove thus much, they make the <hi>Catholick Church Viſible</hi> to be <hi>one Govern'd Society,</hi> or <hi>Body Politick,</hi> which muſt neceſſarily be under a <hi>Gover<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned Head,</hi> either of <hi>One ſingle Perſon,</hi> or of many <hi>Collectively;</hi> whereby they run ſo far, as to deſtroy not only <hi>Congregatio<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal Churches,</hi> but to ſubvert that very <hi>Prin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciple,</hi> upon which the <hi>Reformation</hi> was be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gun in this <hi>Land,</hi> and do lay a Foundation for that <hi>Papal Anti-chriſtian</hi> Power, which
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:66396:42"/> in its <hi>Exerciſe,</hi> hath ſhed the Blood of Thouſands, who are now under the <hi>Al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tar,</hi> crying, <hi>How long</hi> Holy <hi>and</hi> True <hi>dost thou not Avenge,</hi> &amp;c. and againſt which, we have, by the <hi>Oath of Supremacy</hi> Sworn: So that tho' we agree with our <hi>Claſſical Brethren</hi> of <hi>Scotland,</hi> in affirming <hi>Biſhops</hi> and <hi>Presbyters</hi> to be <hi>of the ſame Order,</hi> (which only is againſt the <hi>Divine,</hi> not REGAL <hi>Right</hi> of <hi>Epiſcopacy</hi>) and do great<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Honour them for their Zeal againſt <hi>Su<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perſtition,</hi> and <hi>Profaneneſs,</hi> and for their <hi>Soundneſs</hi> in the <hi>Faith;</hi> yet muſt declare, in the Words of Mr. <hi>Baxter,</hi> [in his <hi>Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>courſe</hi> againſt the <hi>Revolt</hi> to a <hi>Foreign Ju<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſdiction,</hi> which would be to <hi>England,</hi> its PERJURY, CHURCH-RUINE, <hi>and</hi> SLAVERY, <hi>Pag.</hi> 365.] <hi>That we are Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſed with thoſe</hi> Scots, <hi>that have cauſeleſly Quarrell'd with the</hi> Oath of Supremacy, <hi>and</hi> SO HELPT TO <hi>Open a Door to a</hi> FO<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>REIGN JURISDICTION, <hi>which the King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom is Sworn against.</hi> And therefore we cannot, in Confcience, have any Hand in ſetting it up in this Nation. However we muſt do 'em ſo much Juſtice as to add,</p>
                  <pb n="75" facs="tcp:66396:42"/>
               </div>
               <div n="25" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.25. That we are fully perſwaded, their Soundneſs in the <hi>Faith</hi> is ſuch, that they will never approve of the late <hi>Claſſical Project,</hi> as 'tis deſigned by ſome of its <hi>Contrivers.</hi> The true Faith hath obtain'd ſo great an Intereſt in their Hearts, that they'll never be wheedled to joyn in the ſame <hi>Comprehenſion</hi> with either <hi>Quaker,</hi> or <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarian,</hi> tho' they pretend a <hi>Zeal</hi> for the <hi>Claſſical Government.</hi> If then the late <hi>Projectors</hi> propoſe their <hi>Model</hi> with an Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pectation to <hi>decoy</hi> our <hi>Scotch</hi> Brethren into a Complyance with it, they will find them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves, I doubt not, to have greatly failed in their <hi>Politicks;</hi> ſeeing, in the Iſſue, their <hi>Project</hi> cannot but appear to be as <hi>vain,</hi> as the <hi>
                        <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nitarians</hi> threatning the <hi>Church of England</hi> to be for the <hi>Claſſical way,</hi> is <hi>Ridi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>culous,</hi> which yet they have done, as may be ſeen in their <hi>Agreement</hi> with the <hi>Catho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick Church,</hi> P. 13. where it's thus: <q rend="inline">I wiſh the Church had not given, and may never give cauſe to the <hi>
                           <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nita<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rians,</hi> either by <hi>Excluſion,</hi> or <hi>Perſecution,</hi> to have Recourſe to Mr. <hi>Calvin</hi>'s Expe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient.</q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="76" facs="tcp:66396:43"/>
               </div>
               <div n="26" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.26. I might here take notice by whom this <hi>Claſſical</hi> Model was hatch'd, and how it was nouriſh'd under the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment and Warrant of a late State-Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter, and was, in its firſt Projection to be of the ſame Extent and Comprehenſion with the <hi>Friendly Society,</hi> that there might be a more eaſie Coaleſcence, when it ſhould be moſt for the Advantage of thoſe that were at the Head of it. But to be o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver nice in the Enquiry, were to make the thing it ſelf <hi>now</hi> too conſiderable. For whatever might have been expected from ſo hopeful a Deſign, whilſt it was to be carried on with all poſſible <hi>Privacy,</hi> it has the Misfortune, like ſome <hi>Medicines,</hi> and <hi>Perfumes,</hi> to loſe both its Virtue and Savour too, by being expoſed to the open Air. But, if we conſider it in the firſt Contrivance, it would be hard to give an Inſtance of a more Bold and Undigeſted Undertaking ever attempted by Thinking Men, which makes it the more ſurprizing to find a Stateſman tampering with it, were it not that ſome Men delight in <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>radoxes,</hi> of which of late Years, we have had not a few Inſtances; and how far it is from being one, to think either, that our
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:66396:43"/> Brethren in <hi>Scotland</hi> could be prevail'd up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on by theſe Gentlemen, or the Orthodox Church of <hi>England</hi> frighted with the Ghoſt of a <hi>Claſſical</hi> Government; I leave Wiſer Men to judge.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div type="conclusion">
               <head>To Conclude.</head>
               <div n="27" type="subsection">
                  <p>§.27. When our Governours, in their great Wiſdom, ſhall conſider how ſtrong<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly the Principles of the <hi>Engliſh Presbyteri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans,</hi> and <hi>Congregationaliſts,</hi> do Oblige 'em to confine themſelves to <hi>Matters meerly Spiritual,</hi> in <hi>their ſingle Congregations,</hi> how many Barriers are in purſuance of their Principles, ſet up againſt their In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>termedling with the <hi>National Church Form;</hi> and that the very Government, from which alone they are in danger, if it ſhould prevail, would at the ſame time deſtroy that Church Form, for which we plead, will be fully ſatisfied in that Security our Principles do give unto them. Nor can we think, that our Nobility and Gentry will be fond of a <hi>Jure Divino</hi> National Church Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment of any ſort, much leſs of the
<pb n="78" facs="tcp:66396:44"/> 
                     <hi>Claſſical;</hi> which tho' it hath been in moſt Eſteem amongſt the <hi>Presbyterian</hi> Nobi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lity and Gentry in <hi>Scotland,</hi> yet now is become too heavy a Yoak for them to bear; who therefore have lately diſco<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vered their disbelief of its <hi>Divine Right,</hi> by a <hi>Legal</hi> Eſtabliſhment of ſeveral <hi>Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rochian Congregational Churches,</hi> exempt from the <hi>Claſſical</hi> Government; which they would never have done, had they been of Opinion, that the Claſſical way was injoyned them by a <hi>Divine <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terable Law;</hi> ſo that as the Divine Right of the <hi>Claſſical Presbytery</hi> could never be Eſtabliſhed in <hi>England,</hi> in like manner it's not like to continue much longer in <hi>Scotland.</hi> And, conſidering the true State of Affairs Eccleſiaſtical, at this time, we have good Reaſon to hope, That as the <hi>Divine Right</hi> of any other National Church Government, never yet gained a Legal Settlement amongſt us, ſo it never will; and that there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore we may, upon good Grounds, rec<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kon our ſelves to be, in point of our <hi>Liberty, Safe:</hi> For, as our Principles won't ſuffer us to harm the Church; ſo our <hi>Legiſlators</hi> will never bring them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves and <hi>Poſterity</hi> into the Bondage of
<pb n="79" facs="tcp:66396:44"/> any <hi>Jure Divino</hi> National Church, upon which Account, and no other, can they think themſelves obliged to diſquiet <hi>Peaceable Diſſenters.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
